<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Syrophænissa or, the Cananitish womans conflicts in twelue seuerall tractats discouered, sectio prima. At Horndon on the hil, in the countie of Essex. 1598. Dulcescit Christus, amarescit mundus R.W.</title>
            <author>R. W. (Robert Wilmot), fl. 1568-1608.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1601</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15500</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25765</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102527</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838304</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838304</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2678</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15500)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2678)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1088:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Syrophænissa or, the Cananitish womans conflicts in twelue seuerall tractats discouered, sectio prima. At Horndon on the hil, in the countie of Essex. 1598. Dulcescit Christus, amarescit mundus R.W.</title>
                  <author>R. W. (Robert Wilmot), fl. 1568-1608.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Valentine Simmes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R.W. = Robert Wilmot.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The conflicts of the woman of Canaan.</note>
                  <note>Contains only Tractates 1-6.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2678:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2678:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Syrophaeniſſa</hi> OR, <hi>The Cananitiſh Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans conflicts:</hi> In twelue ſeuerall Tractats diſcouered, <hi>Sectio prima.</hi> At Horndon on the hil, in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Eſſex. 1598.</p>
            <p> 
               <hi>Dulceſcit Christus, Amareſcit Mundus</hi> R. W.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London by Valentine Simmes, 1601.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2678:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2678:2"/>
            <head>To the Right <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull his louing</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, Maſter Gabriell Poyntzs
<hi>Eſquier, health and true</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines in this life, and in the life to come through Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I call to minde, (Right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull) the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it hath pleaſed Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie GOD to bleſſe mee, by thoſe ſecondarie meanes of my maintenance, which I haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, vnder his gratious prouidence
<pb facs="tcp:2678:3"/> from you, I can not, but in the humblenes of my ſoule acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge with all thankfulnes of hart, his diuine goodnes, and I account it alſo a part of my duetie, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge ſome kindnes and ſeruice vnto you. Wherefore, in reſpect of the many benefites reaped by your Wor. accept, I pray you, this ſimple trauell, the firſt fruites of my deuinitie, your Schollers New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeeres gift, preſenting his entire and hartie affection towardes you: which at your leaſure, may it pleaſe you to pervſe, and if you ſhall eſteeme this worth the view of the world, hereafter (it may be) I ſhall be perſwaded to paſſe the reſt to the publike print.</p>
            <p>The rather, becauſe of late, I chaunced to light vpon a very ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous report, which an vnkind Countryman of ours doth inflict vpon vs in that immodeſt Preface before the laſt edition vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:2678:3"/> Chriſtian directorie.</p>
            <p>Wherein the Authour confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently auerreth, that we the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpell (whom it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his fatherhood to terme Sciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes and Heretikes) can ſet forth no Bookes of true deuotion, profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to godlie life. And he bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not to render a three fold reaſon therof: the one drawne from the teſtimonie of S. <hi>Paul</hi> the 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> the other from S. <hi>Peter.</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. and the third againe from S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſo concludeth, that we are all but moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers and deceiuers, when we talke of Mortification and a quickning ſpirit, for ſaith he (to vſe his owne wordes) they can not preach this point of true pietie, vnleſſe they ſhould impugne the principall Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of their owne doctrine.</p>
            <p>What ſhalbe done vnto thee O thou falſe tongue? the Lord ſhall iudge thee, did I delight in this defamatorie kind of declayming I
<pb facs="tcp:2678:4"/> could annatomize ſome of our Gentlemen like Ieſuits, in their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie pleaſant prankes ſo conceited, as would eaſilie procure the moſt mortified Catholike of <hi>Rome</hi> to bluſh and ſmile.</p>
            <p>Is it a ſmall matter, publikelie, and in print, ſo ſhamefully to belie and ſcandalize an whole eſtate of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme? but, <hi>Quid non audet paterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas vestra?</hi> ſufficeth vs we ſtand or fall to our God; &amp; we paſſe very li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to be iudged by you, or of mans iudgement, he that iudgeth vs is the Lord, who will make the counſels of the heart manifeſt, and then ſhall euery man haue his praiſe of God.</p>
            <p>But if it had pleaſed his Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to haue conferred with ſome of his own Catholike brethren con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this matter, they would (no doubt) haue freelie confeſſed vnto him (as they haue found the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of true Mortification in ſome of their houſes, where they haue bin
<pb facs="tcp:2678:4"/> priuate priſoners, though it were not in the wearing of the haire, nor in voluntarie ſcourging of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Howſoeuer this man plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him ſelfe and the brethren of his owne broode with theſe forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: Yet he that commeth with any reuerence to the reading of this Pamphlet, ſhall confeſſe, that we can preach and teach true Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> was eſteemed (and that worthilie) a noble Prince, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt he ſtood in
<hi>Megabizus</hi> ſchoole, and ſaid nothing, but when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to talke idlelie of thoſe things hee knew not, the Schoolmaſter told him, that euen his litle children would laugh him to ſcorne.</p>
            <p>I am loath to trouble your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with a number of vaine wordes, for I perceiue, in many wordes there may be many ſlips, and ſo many trippes taken.</p>
            <p>I commend this firſt aduenture
<pb facs="tcp:2678:5"/> of halfe my ſubſtance vnto the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of your fauourable iudiciall iudgement. And ſo I commit you and yours vnto the tui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of th' almightie for euer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Wor. poore ſcholler R. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2678:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Chriſtian</hi> cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reader, increaſe of all ſpiritual bleſſings and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall benefits.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ountrymen, and my beloued, in the bowelles of Chriſt Ieſus, theſe Chips (for ſo they haue beene tearmed) of Diuinitie, I neuer purpoſed ſhould haue come to the open light and ſight of this worlde; but being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly taken (when they were deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered) from me and then promiſed to the Preſſe, I (rather than they ſhoulde come foorth ſo maymed) was reſolued (too raſhly) to peruſe, and ſo to publiſh them: with what labour they are wreſted and wrung from me, and with what difficultie now at the laſt they are authentically allowed your ſight, I am coniured,
<pb facs="tcp:2678:6"/> not to diſcouer<hi>:</hi> ſuch as they are, I humbly commend to the ſucceſſe of Gods bleſſing, and your fauora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble acceptance. Onely this I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not paſſe ouer, which mightily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayled with me, a Sentence which I then called to minde I had ſomtime read in
<hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> If (ſaith hee) the godly minded Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian may not publiſh his holy wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, wherfore were Letters inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? May the Epicure ſend abroad diſhoneſt things? The Macheuilian his Policies, and the baſe Ballet-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker his Rithmes, and ſhall not the ſimple learned (but true hearted Chriſtian) ſet foorth ſuch things as may for euer be profitable?</p>
            <p>Againe, ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi> in his ſixt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, If Wiſedome her ſelfe were graunted vnto me, on this conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to ſhut her vppe faſt, and make my priuate vſe of her, but neuer to publiſh her, I woulde vtterly refuſe her, for priuate wiſedome is but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
<pb facs="tcp:2678:6"/> ſingularitie.</p>
            <p>Heerewithall ſomewhat anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yet I could not but maruel, that in the church of God heere in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> where there are ſo many, indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſuch ſingular gifts and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Gods holy Spirite, there ſhould be too many found, that will not be perſwaded to publiſh, their moſt excellent and exquiſit labors, to the common benefite of others; whereas they ſee, and may marke, the principall cauſe whereby the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> beginnes to ſeem glorious at this day, is, for that they that haue the moſt plauſible wittes, and pleaſing gifts amongſt them, as <hi>Bellarmine, Granatenſis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Stella, Ferus</hi> and our
<hi>Parſons,</hi> with ſuch others, whatſoeuer they haue laboured in, they haue publiſhed and diſperſed abroade.</p>
            <p>But our admirable Diuines, hold it a baſe indignitie, that their graue ſtudies ſhoulde come to the cenſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:2678:7"/> of euery Lay mans reading: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can I iuſtly blame them, for what through the ſwarme of Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts that increaſe by the heate of the Sunne, like Frogges in Summer, harted on too much, by ſome of too good calling.</p>
            <p>And what for the number of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy prying Papiſtes, that generally miſlike all the Treatiſes of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie whatſoeuer, that by any of the Miniſters of the Goſpell are publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
            <p>And what for the crowde of our purer Puritanes, that allowe of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but what they of their owne brotherhoode ſhall broach. And laſtly, what through our prating Proteſtants that neuer commend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Treatiſe of Diuinitie, longer than they ſhall runningly reade it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and marke the mans methode and wit that made it: thou heauenly Theologie mayeſt be perchaunce reuerently regarded, whileſt thou
<pb facs="tcp:2678:7"/> arte for an houre, with ſweet vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and graue geſture deliuered: but if euer thou com to the publike Preſſe, thou ſhalt feele and finde thy ſelfe too publickely oppreſſed, by the multitude of theſe thy malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ennemies.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe, I could wiſh from my heart, that in theſe diuine Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, if any things iuſtly miſlike the Reader (as many things may) he woulde remember Saint <hi>Paules</hi> counſell, to followe the trueth in loue, conſiddering, as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, In many things we may erre all of vs.</p>
            <p>The God of all trueth (I hope) will ſo bleſſe theſe Labours in the trueth, that whoſoeuer commeth not with a preiudicate contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conceit, to the reading of theſe Concluſions, hee ſhall, wyth the ſtrength of this ſmall Cake, and wyth the comforte of this colde wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, walke foorth with <hi>Elias,</hi> euen
<pb facs="tcp:2678:8"/> to <hi>Horeb,</hi> the Mountaine of GOD: And thus I leaue thee, committing theſe my firſt fruites vnto the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Gods holy Spirite, who grant vs a right vnderſtanding hart, wyth a charitable friendly iudgement in all things.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. Wilmott.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:2678:8"/>
            <head>The Cananitiſh womans Conflicts.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Matth. 15. verſe 21.</bibl>
               <q>Then Ieſus went thence, and departed into the Borders of Tyrus and Sydon.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD (ſaith <note place="margin">1. Corin. 1. verſ. 27. 28.</note> the apoſtle) hath choſen the fooliſhe things of this world, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founde the Wiſe, the weake things of the worlde, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the mighty; and vile things, which are deſpiſed, hath God cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, to bring to naught, things that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2678:9"/> are. And this hath beene the Lords practiſe of olde; for by <hi>Huſhai</hi> hee <note place="margin">2. Samu. 17. 8</note> effatuated the counſell of wiſe
<hi>Ahi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thophel:</hi> by <hi>Dauids</hi> weake meanes, he brought downe mightie <hi>Goliah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> and by deſpiſed <hi>Iphtah,</hi> vile in the eyes of his brethren, he vanquiſhed <note place="margin">Iudg. 11. 33.</note> the huge hoſte of the <hi>Ammonites.</hi> But if yee deſire in one perſon to ſee all theſe three things palpably per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, looke then into this hiſtory, and conſider with me, howe by this fooliſh, weak, and deſpiſed woman, the Lord hath confounded, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the wiſe, the mighty, and the ſcornefull generation of the Iewes.</p>
            <p>Therefore (ſaieth <hi>Auſten)</hi> this <note place="margin">Auſtin ſer. 74.</note> memorable hiſtorie is neuer to bee forgotten; for it ſerueth as a liuely mirrour of true godlineſſe: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in an inuincible faith may be ſeene lincked to an humbled ſpirit: and I haue obſerued in the diſcourſe of this Storie, fiue notable pointes for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2678:9"/> our inſtruction, well woorthy eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall remembrance.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the miſerable condition of our naturall man, which is ſuch, as is not onely ſubiect to the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the diuell, but alſo, to his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame torments, and that euen in this life.</p>
            <p>Secondly, with what faith, feare, and reuerence, Ieſus Chriſt our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour is to be ſought after, for helpe and ſuccour in this life.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, what greeuous tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and domeſticall afflictions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne for the elect of God, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time to be winnowed withall in this life.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, what louely care, and carefull loue, Parents and Tutors ought to haue, of the children com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their charge, as alſo, what a charitable minde euery Chriſtian ought to beare towards his afflicted neighbour.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, the triumphant victorie,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2678:10"/> and healthfull rewarde, wherewith our inuincible faith is crowned.</p>
            <p>Theſe thinges ſo excellent, ſo comfortable, and ſo worthy the lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning. I beſeech you accept as friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as they come from the ground of a kinde heart vnto yee.</p>
            <p>The Euangeliſt aimeth at theſe two markes, and hitteth them both in this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The one is a moſt euident proof of the deitie in Chriſt Ieſus, who with his very woord caſteth out vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene diuells, and healeth her (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out applying any thing vnto her) whom he neuer beheld.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The other is, the inuincible faith of a weake woman, greeuouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted ſince her conuerſion to the true religion of God.</p>
            <p>In theſe wordes (which are vſed as an induction vnto this hiſtorie) the holy-ghoſt ſeemeth orderly to obſerue theſe three deſcriptions.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, the Chronographie or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2678:10"/> of the time when this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle was wrought:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the <hi>Topographie</hi> or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the place where it was wrought.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the <hi>Proſopographie</hi> or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the perſon vpon whom it was wrought.</p>
            <p>Our Sauiour Chriſt had been in the land of <hi>Gennezaret,</hi> and thither came the Scribes, Phariſes, and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Ieruſalem, with a great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, vnto him, of purpoſe to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell with him, and to catch him or his Diſciples in a ſnare.</p>
            <p>But when he had roundly threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them with the iudgements of God, and ſoundly laid open vnto them the naturall filthineſſe of their owne harts: then ſaith the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt, Ieſus went thence, that is, from <hi>Genezaret</hi> (as appeareth) and came into the coaſts of <hi>Tire</hi> and <hi>Sidon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Thus may we read that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt was twice forced
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2678:11"/> to depart and leaue their companie, amongſt whom he was working the will of his father: once was from the <hi>Gaderenes,</hi> and that was becauſe of <note place="margin">Mark. 5. 17.</note> their Couetouſnes; for they feared the looſing of their Swine.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> An o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was in this place from the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of Ieruſalem, becauſe of the contempt &amp; hardnes of their harts: ſo that theſe two things will enforce Chriſt Ieſus to depart from our companie, and to leaue our coaſts. Couetouſnes &amp; Contempt; the one ſauoureth too much of groſſe Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, and the other ſmelleth of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Atheiſme, Two things which the Lord abhorreth.</p>
            <p>Therefore he ſaith, for his wicked couetouſnes I am angry with him, I <note place="margin">Eſay 57. 17</note> haue hid my ſelfe, &amp; am gone away. And of the three caueats in the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell which our Sauiour Chriſt hath <note place="margin">Luke 12, 15.</note> giuen vnto vs, this is one, Take heed and beware of Couetouſnes<hi>:</hi> for though a man haue abundance, yet
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2678:11"/> his life (or ſafetie) ſtandeth not in his riches.</p>
            <p>Hereuppon dooth the Authour <note place="margin">Hebr. 13. 5.</note> of the Epiſtle to the Hebrewes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort all Chriſtians, that their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation be without Couetouſnes, deſiring them to be content with that they haue: for (ſaith he) the Lord hath ſaid, <hi>Non deſeram, neque deſtituam,</hi> I will not faile thee, nor forſake thee.</p>
            <p>The Lion (they ſay) cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the ſauour of an hogge, but whether it be ſo or no, this I am ſure of, The victorious Lion of the tribe of Iuda cannot abide the ſmell of Couetouſnes.</p>
            <p>The other thing that driues Chriſt Ieſus our Sauiour out of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie and Countrie, is contempt &amp; hardnes of heart, which is alwaies the fore-runner of confuſion. And of all kind of people, there are none ſo much taxed with this fault, as Phariſes, Lawyers and Hypocrites,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2678:12"/> of whom the holy ghoſt ſaith, They deſpiſed the counſel of God againſt <note place="margin">Luk. 7. 30.</note> them ſelues. But to meet with the contemptuous deſpiſers, the Lord e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacted a very good ſtatute, &amp; that is this: He that blaſphemeth the Lord, or ſpeaketh preſumptuouſly, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuouſly <note place="margin">Numb. 15.
31</note> of his holy word, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be borne in the land, or a ſtranger, he ſhall die the death. The reaſon is added, becauſe he deſpiſed the word of the Lord: Therefore doth the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> exhort the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> neither to deſpiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecying, <note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 4. 8.</note> nor the Prophet: for (ſaith he) he that deſpiſeth theſe things, deſpiſeth not man, but God: and in this reſpect our Sauior Chriſt war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranteth the departure of his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples <note place="margin">Math. 10. 14</note> from that place, and from that people, which neither reuerently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them, nor regard their words; proteſting, it ſhall be eaſier for the land of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorra</hi> in the day of iudgement, then for that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2678:12"/> place, and people.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee what driueth Chriſt Ieſus our Lord out of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie &amp; coaſts: and ye know, when the Prince remoueth, all the honour of the court departeth with him: So, when our Sauiour Chriſt depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth from vs, all his graces and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly bleſſings take their fare-well of vs: for when the Lord departeth from <hi>Saul,</hi> by and by an euill ſpirit
<note place="margin">1. Samu. 16. 14.</note> poſſeſſeth &amp; vexeth him: As when the Sun is fallen from our Horizon, darknes couereth the face of the whole earth.</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, let vs deteſt Couetouſnes, and beware of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, for where theſe two infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous plagues are nouriſhed, our Lord Ieſus Chriſt cannot abide to ſtay within their noyſome ſauours.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Now followeth the ſecond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the place wherunto our Lord Ieſus went; He departed into the coaſts of <hi>Tirus</hi> and <hi>Sidon.</hi> Theſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2678:13"/> two Cities were great ſea townes, or markets of exchange, mightilie fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented, rich and populous, yea, and famous to the verie dayes of S. Ierome; they were ſcituated in the region of <hi>Phoenitia,</hi> bordering vpon the vttermoſt parts of
<hi>Paleſtine,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining <note place="margin">Ioſua 19. 28. 29.</note> the boundes of the try be of <hi>Aſhur,</hi> ſouthward. Into theſe coaſts, that is, into the borders or ſuburbes of theſe cities came Chriſt Ieſus at this time.</p>
            <p>But it may be asked wherfore our Sauiour ſhould goe to this place: <note place="margin">Obiectio</note> whereas he had heretofore charged his Diſciples, not to go into the way <note place="margin">Matth. 10. 5</note> of the Gentiles, neither to enter into the Citie of the
<hi>Samaritans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be anſwered, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt it was <note place="margin">Responſio</note> not a fit ſeaſon for them as yet to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake ſo great a labour; but vnto him, now was the hower and fulnes of the ſeaſon come to do his fathers will<hi>:</hi> for now, when he ſaw this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion began to be white vnto the <note place="margin">Iohn 4. 35.</note>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2678:13"/> harueſt, therfore was the ſickle to be thruſt in.</p>
            <p>Againe, he would not haue them to go into the way of the Gentiles, to preach, or to bring vnto them, the glad tydings of the Goſpell: Neither doth he come hither at this time, to that purpoſe, but as Saint <hi>Marke</hi> hath it, he came to be alone, <note place="margin">Mark. 7.
24.</note> neither would he that any man ſhould haue knowen of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</p>
            <p>But there are two ſpeciall reaſons to be giuen which moued our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour to go to this place:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The one is (ſaith S. <hi>Chryſost.) Palam &amp; aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta.</hi> The other is
<hi>ſecreta &amp; incognita.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The one is plainely to be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which was to refreſh, and eaſe himſelfe after his weariſome labors amongſt the Iewes; for this cauſe he entred into a priuate houſe in the Suburbs, to be obſcure for a ſeaſon, in a place where he was not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en; prefiguring thereby, in a myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2678:14"/> the ruinous fall of the ſynagog, and the beautifull erection of the church of God amongſt the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</p>
            <p>But if this weake body where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with our ſauior Chriſt was clothed, had neede of the refreſhing of his tyred members, what vnnaturall men are they, that will not alowe to his miniſters, (men of as weak con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution as our ſauiour Chriſt was) their chriſtian recreation?</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle ſaint <hi>Paule,</hi> as hee chargeth vs to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, labourers, ſo alſo he woulde haue vs <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, louers of our labours: but he that is tired like an horſe in the mill, or an oxe in the plough, cannot long loue his labours, and then woe be to him that dooth the worke of the Lorde <note place="margin">Ierem. 48. verſ. 10.</note> negligently.</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is: It is both godly and lawfull for the miniſter of the Goſpell, when hee feeleth himſelfe weary in his holy labours,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2678:14"/> to refreſh himſelfe with ſome chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian recreation, ſo it be doone (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Sauiours example in this place) diſcreetely.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The other reaſon which moued our Sauiour, at that time, to come to theſe coaſts, was vnknowen to the world, but well knowne to him, before whom the extreame minute of the laſt houre is preſent, and that was to bring to light to the publike view of the whole worlde, the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull faith that was in this weake woman, ſo rudely, ſo idolatrouſly, and ſo ignorantly brought vp: and yet nowe in the firſt fruites of her knowledge, ſo vehemently, ſo reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly, and ſo learnedly conflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Chriſt Ieſus. Wherefore, as <hi>Elias</hi> had a hartier welcome of the poore widdow of <hi>Zareptah</hi> then of <note place="margin">1. Reg.
17.</note> 
               <hi>Ahab,</hi> and all his counſellors: ſo are the mercies of our ſauior Chriſt, more magnified by this miſerable woman, than by all the Rabbies of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2678:15"/> the Iews: for ſuch is the bleſſed vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines <note place="margin">Luk. 1.
53.</note> ſong. He hath filled the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with good things, and the rich he hath ſent emptie away.</p>
            <p>But let vs therein conſidder the wonderful ſecret of Gods wiſedom, whileſt our Lord Ieſus Chriſt wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked openly in the land of Iewrie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the peculiar people, vnto whome hee was ſpecially ſent, allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all men vnto him; hee findeth but few that regarde his proffered grace: but ſo ſoone as hee ſteppes out of Iewry towarde the Gentiles, deſiring not to be knowen, behold how quickely he is found out, and his louing kindeneſſe moſt thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully receiued. So falleth it foorth with vs euen in theſe dayes, marke yee not howe the ſweete ſecrets of Gods word are hidne from the wiſe <note place="margin">Math. 11. 25. et ver.
5.</note> and prudent of this worlde? And are reuealed vnto babes and ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and the poore, very ioyfully and greedily receiue the gladde ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2678:15"/> of the Goſpell, ſuch is the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine wiſedome, pleaſure, and will of our heauenly Father; to him bee glorie, Amen.</p>
            <argument>
               <p>¶ <hi>Haec rerum capita in hoc Tractatu, vt in reliquis, in longiorem oratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem dilata, &amp; auditoribus applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta fuêre, quae nunc de industria ſolummodo capitulata &amp; abbreui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ata ſunt.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="treatise">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:2678:16"/>
            <head>Tractatus ſecundus</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Verſe 22.</bibl>
               <q>And behold, a woman, a Canaanite, came out of the ſame coastes, and cryed, ſaying:</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E are now come to the third deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription of the perſon, vppon whome, or for whoſe ſake this ſame miracle was wrought. In the which deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wee haue orderly theſe foure poyntes to be examined:</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the Euangeliſt ſayeth, ſhe was a <hi>Woman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>a Cananite,</hi> or a Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiſh woman.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſhee came, <hi>out of the ſame coasts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, ſhe <hi>cryed, ſaying, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:2678:16"/> But firſt, in that the Holy-ghoſt vſeth this watchwoorde
<hi>Beholde:</hi> which is a word of admiration and attention. Whereſoeuer you meete with it throgh the whole Scriptures of God, noting ſome rare and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull matter, well worthy the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation which inſueth, as in that where the Prophet ſayth, <hi>Behold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 7. 14</note> 
               <hi>a Virgin ſhall conceiue and bring forth her ſonne.</hi> And againe, that which Saint Iohn Baptiſt ſaith, <hi>Behold the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 1. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lamb of God that taketh away the ſins of the world, &amp;c.</hi> in the reſt.</p>
            <p>Here then our Euangeliſt mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſet downe a maruellous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; to deliuer a wondrous thing, he ſaith, Beholde. Let vs then, as we are warned by this watchword, lift vp the eyes of our minde, marke, conſider, and beholde this woman.</p>
            <p>A woman, not ſuch a one as was <hi>Sarah,</hi> who laughed at the promiſes of God in the incredulitie <note place="margin">Geneſ. 18. 12</note> of her heart: but ſuch a one as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2678:17"/> beyond all hope; and beleeued, contrary to the reaſon of beleefe.</p>
            <p>A woman, not ſuch a one as was <hi>Iobs</hi> wife, who when ſhe ſawe <note place="margin">Iob 2. 9.</note> her husband puniſhed of the Lord (ſhe that ſhould haue bin his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter) beginnes to be his confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, giuing him counſell, to curſſe God, and die. But ſuch a one, as ſeeing her daughter tormented of the Diuell, runneth to GOD for helpe, and with her importunate prayers neuer leaues him, vntil ſhe was releaſed and eaſed.</p>
            <p>A woman, whereby we are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to learne, the things, which by nature are very weake, God vſeth (by grace) to make ſtrong. For <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Geneſ. 32. 28</note> though hee halt in his thigh, yet is hee made the Iſrael of God: and it is moſt true which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle teſtifieth of the Saints of God in elder time, who of weake became <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 34</note> very ſtrong. And Saint <hi>Paule</hi> had the experience thereof, hee ſpake
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2678:17"/> therfore that he had proued, where he ſaith, <hi>When I am weake, then am</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 10. 12</note> 
               <hi>I ſtrong.</hi> Truly therfore and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſingeth <hi>Anna</hi> in her heauenly <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2</note> ſong; the weake haue girded them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with ſtrength, as in little <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> weake <hi>Iudeth,</hi> and lame
<hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiboſheth</hi> may be ſeene.</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is with the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, Gods ſtrength is made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <note place="margin">2. Cor. 12. 9</note> in our weakeneſſe. Lette vs learne then (wee that are ſtrong in faith) to ſupport them that are yet weak, that they may gather ſtrength in the Lord Ieſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[A Canaanite]</hi> The ſecond <note place="margin">Marke 7. 26</note> point to be obſerued in the deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this perſon, <hi>S. Marke</hi> calleth her a Greeke, which was a common name applied to all the Gentiles, ſhe is ſaid alſo to be a <hi>Syropheniſsian</hi> by nation, which was the place of her dwelling.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chananea</hi> is by interpretation <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutata,</hi> and truely euery ſoule that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2678:18"/> ſeeketh for help and ſuccour of our Lord Ieſus, muſt be (with this good woman) one changed, altered, and metamorphoſed, turned from euill to good, from vice to vertue, from prophanenes to holines, a right Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanite. Alſo ſome of the Fathers haue interpreted <hi>Syropheniſſa,</hi> to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie <hi>profunde conuerſa,</hi> deepelie, ſoundly, &amp; one ſincerely conuerted.</p>
            <p>In this <hi>Syropheniſſian</hi> we haue then a notable example of a true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant ſinner ſyncerely conuerted. And by both theſe brands ſet vpon her, we find ſhe deſcended of the poſteritie of <hi>Cham,</hi> the father of <note place="margin">Geneſ. 9. 25</note>
               <hi>Canaan</hi> curſed by the Prophet: Whereby we gather, that which by nature is curſed, by faith may be made bleſſed, ſanctified, and ſaued. For though the waters of <hi>Marah</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 15. 25.</note> were by nature bitter, yet through <hi>Moſes</hi> prayers by grace from aboue they became ſweet and healthfull. By this was <hi>Rahab</hi> the common
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2678:18"/> harlot of <hi>Iericho</hi> ſanctified and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. <note place="margin">Ioſhua 6. 22</note> And through this our Sauior Chriſt ſaith, that many lewd Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans and vile ſinners ſhall enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">Math. 21. 32.</note> the kingdome of God. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, we are all by nature the children of wrath, as well as others: <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2</note> but by faith in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord, we are ſeaſoned and ſweetned with the ſauour of eternall life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Came out of the ſame coaſts.]</hi> This is the third point to be obſerued in this deſcription. Wherein we are giuen, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, to learne that God hath his elect ſome times amongſt the reprobates in <hi>Tire</hi> and <hi>Sidon:</hi> for <note place="margin">Reuel. 2. 13</note> the Lord ſaith to his Church of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamus,</hi> that ſhe dwelleth euen where <hi>Sathans</hi> throne is. As the Arke of God was ſometime in the temple of
<hi>Dagon:</hi> for good wheat growes in <note place="margin">1. Sam. 5</note> the middeſt of tares, and ſometime ſweet roſes ſpring &amp; ſprout vp from a bank of ſtinging and ſtincking nettles. Did not righteous <hi>Lot</hi> dwel
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2678:19"/> in <hi>Sodom,</hi> the ſinke of ſinne, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in Egypt, and
<hi>Daniel</hi> in Babylon? but to touch pitch and not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed with all, to liue in the midſt of a naughtie and crooked nation, and to ſhine amongſt them as bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome lights,
<hi>Hic labor, hoc opus,</hi> this is praiſe worthy: for a Monke to liue vertuous in a wilderneſſe, or an <hi>Anchoriſt</hi> holie, locked vp in a ſtone wall, is not worth the wonder.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, we are giuen to learne out of theſe words, that they that will meete with our Sauiour Chriſt to their health and ſaluation, muſt come out of their owne coaſts, they muſt leaue their old conſort and company. <hi>Abraham</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 12. 1</note> to come out of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and from his kinred, and from his fathers houſe, to go into the land which the Lord ſhould giue him. And
<hi>Moſes</hi> muſt come out of <hi>Egypt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 2. 1.</note> before he come vnto the mountain of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:2678:19"/> 
               <hi>Lot</hi> (as loath as he is) muſt leaue <note place="margin">Geneſ. 19. marke 5. 2</note> 
               <hi>Sodom,</hi> if he will be ſaued<hi>:</hi> and the mad man poſſeſſed of the diuells muſt come out of the graues before he meeteth with Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>Let vs alſo labour to come out of our ſelues, to leaue our old dwellings in ſinne, to forſake our naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, to flie from our owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires (to whom we are ſo neere allied) that we may meete with Ieſus our true Sauiour.</p>
            <p>Phiſitions vſe three ſpeciall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to perſwade a ſick man, for the recouery of his health to remooue his dwelling.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, the groſſnes of the aire: but I aſſure you there is no aire ſo contagious to the bodie, as ſinne is infectious to the ſoule.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, the incommodious ſcituation of the place, or houſe: but there is no earthlie manſion, which ſtandeth ſo dangerous, as that ſoule that liues in ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:2678:20"/> The third is, the vnkind neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood about him: but what neighbours may be ſo barbarous to the bodie, as the diuell the enuious man is to the ſoule?</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is: for the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie of thy daughter: that is of thy ſoules health (allegoricallie) come out of theſe coaſts, to meete with Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, we are giuen to learne out of theſe wordes, that there are three degrees, or three profitable progreſſes, to be made by them that haue truelie repented them of their ſinnes, and are conuerted vnto our Lord Ieſus.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, with this good wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to come out.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, from her owne coaſtes.</p>
            <p>The third is, to crie out.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, the ſtate of them which begin to repent.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, the ſtate of them
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2678:20"/> that haue repented.</p>
            <p>The third is, the ſtate of them which are ſtill in the practize of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, which becauſe it is the perpetuall exerciſe of a Chriſtian mans life, let vs looke a little better into it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[And cried ſaying,]</hi> Here in the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> firſt place we are giuen to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that this <hi>Canaanitiſh</hi> woman had an excellent faith and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in our Lord Ieſus: for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe (as the Apoſtle ſaith) how can <note place="margin">Rom. 10.
14.</note> they call vpon him in whom they haue not belieued? and how can they belieue in him of whom they haue not heard? Doubtles therfore this good woman had grounded her faith vpon the generall promiſes of God granted vnto the whole world in the promiſed redeemer; as this: All nations in the world ſhall be bleſſed in him. And againe, he ſhal deliuer the poore when he crieth, the needie alſo and him that hath
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2678:21"/> no helper. And againe, he that put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eneſ. 12. 3.</note> his truſt in him ſhall neuer be <note place="margin">Pſal. 72. 12</note> confounded. Theſe promiſes had
<note place="margin">Eſay 28.</note> ſhe heard of, which ſhe knew did ſpecially belong vnto the Meſſiah, and thus ſhe applied them to her ſelfe. If all the nations of the earth ſhall be bleſſed in him, then are not we <hi>Cananits</hi> excluded from this bleſſing. And if he ſhall heare the poore that crie vnto him, then will he heare me ſo poore and helpleſſe a creature as I am. And foraſmuch as whoſoeuer putteth his truſt in him ſhall not be confounded, then ſhall not I be diſappointed of my hope: for I haue repoſed my whole confidence in him.</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, that we thus learne to edifie, and build vp our moſt holy faith, that ſhe being foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and grounded vpon this rocke, may be able to ſtand faſt, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure all the tempeſtuous ſtormes of <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1. 7.</note> temptation, that the triall of our
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2678:21"/> faith, which is much more precious then gold, may be found vnto our praiſe, honour, and glorie, at the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of our Lord Ieſus.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond thing giuen vs to learne, is, the vehemencie of her ſpeech, expreſſed by this word <hi>(cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed)</hi> for a ſtrong faith ſendeth forth earneſt requeſts, as a feeble faith maketh faint praiers, for great miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and perplexities will force forth great out cries. Hence was it that <hi>Moſes,</hi> when he (with the people of
<note place="margin">Exod. 14. 15.</note> Iſraell) was driuen to ſuch an exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent at the red Sea, hauing the mountaines on each ſide of them, their enemies behind them, and the deep before them ready to ſwallow them vp: the Lord asketh him wherefore he doth ſo crie vnto him. Euen ſo good <hi>Hannah,</hi> a woman <note place="margin">1. Sam. 1. 15</note> troubled in her ſpirit, in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexitie of her ſoule, ſhe calleth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord, and wept ſore, ſhee prayeth weeping, and weepeth
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2678:22"/> praying. And what a continuall exerciſe doth the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 61. 6.</note> make of this, as himſelfe teſtifieth? euery night cauſe I my bed to ſwim in my teares, and I water my couch with my weepings. And our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our affirmeth, that his elect crie day <note place="margin">Luk. 18. 7.</note> and night vnto him.</p>
            <p>Beloued, when we pray thus crying, and crie out in our prayers, as <hi>Ezechias</hi> did, chattering like a ſwallow, and mourning like a doue, <note place="margin">Eſay 28. 14.</note> how gratiouſlie the Lord accepteth of theſe our cries, ye may perceiue by <hi>Marie Magdalen,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> that wept bitterlie.</p>
            <p>There are three kinds of praiers ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> which neuer pierce the heauens,
<hi>Timida, tepida, &amp; te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meraria oratio,</hi> a fearfull one which fainteth and vaniſheth like a vapour before the Sunne.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, a luke warme praier, which like a meteor, is neither hote nor cold, neither feruent, nor fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2678:22"/> and that is conſumed ere it come to his centre.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third is a raſh prayer, which furiouſly aſcendeth like a gun-ſhote into the aire, but it falleth downe againe, not onely doing no good, but much harme: and theſe kind of praiers cannot preuaile with the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, but that which is <hi>fidelis, humilis, et feruens,</hi> faithfull, humble, and feruent, out of doubt it neuer returneth from the throne of God emptie to our hungrie ſoules. Here (me thinkes) I might frame this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, that prayer which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feruencie &amp; feeling, is no praier with vnderſtanding: And what prayer ſoeuer is without vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, is no prayer in the ſpirit: and the prayer which is not in the ſpirit, is not acceptable before God. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the prayer which is without feruencie and feeling, is not accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God. Will ye then know the reaſon why ye pray ſo much, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2678:23"/> preuaile not, ye aske ſo often and <note place="margin">Iames 4. 3</note> receiue not, <hi>S. Iames</hi> giues it, becauſe (ſaith he) ye aske amiſſe.</p>
            <p>For indeed we neither aske in the ſame maner, nor in the ſame mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as we ought to do. In the ſame maner ſo faithfullie, in the ſame meaſure ſo feruentlie, pouring out our ſoules like water into the Lords boſome, as it becommeth vs.</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, before thou praieſt, prepare thine hart and ſoule therunto, as the Preacher counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth thee. And when thou praieſt, be not faint harted in thy prayers, but continue in prayer, and watch therunto with all dilligence, and be thou aſſured, as the Angell ſaid to old <hi>Tobias:</hi> ſo will the Lord ſay <note place="margin">Tob 12. 14</note> vnto thy ſoule, thy prayer and thy teares are accepted, and thou haſt found fauour &amp; grace in his ſight.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, this her crie our Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt noteth to be vocall in this word
<hi>ſaying.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:2678:23"/> There is indeed an internall crie of the ſoule, which the Lord highlie delighteth in, as was that which good <hi>Anna</hi> had when ſhe was ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.</note> dronk, but not with the bloud of the grape, but with the wine of true deuotion. And ſo ſaith a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>In Dei auribus deſiderium ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemens magnus est clamor,</hi> A vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deſire is a great crie in the eares of God, according to the old adage,
<hi>Non vox, ſed votum.</hi> And this kind of ſpeaking, though the Lord regardeth (as he did
<hi>Ezechias</hi> chattering) yet is not the labour of the lippes exempted: for the Lord that made both the tongue and the ſpirit, lookes for a tribute to bee paid to him from them both: and for this cauſe is it that the Lord openeth thy lippes, becauſe thy mouth may ſhew forth his praiſe.</p>
            <p>He then that ſpareth the trauell of his tongue, becauſe he hath lifted vp his hart vnto God, he hath bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2678:24"/> the common order of Gods ſeruice, and the Apoſtolicall rule in the order of the primitiue Church which was this, that at all our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and giuing of thanks, the vnlearned ſhould ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="treatise">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:2678:24"/>
            <head>Tractatus tertius.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Verſe 22.</bibl>
               <q>Haue mercy vpon me O Lord thou Sonne of Dauid.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee are now come and proceeded to the words of this crie, wherin the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and likewiſe the cauſe of her crie is diſcouered: her crie is a prayer and her prayer is an outcrie: So that the firſt godlie practiſe of this good womans faith, was a vehement and forcible prayer.</p>
            <p>And if ye aske me what is the continuall exerciſe of a Chriſtian mans life? I anſwere prayer for what ſhould he els do but as the Apoſtle willeth him pray continually, and as
<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5. 17</note> our ſweet Sauiour hath exampled vnto vs, who in the dayes of his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2678:25"/> fleſh, offred vp prayers with ſtrong <note place="margin">Hebr. 5. 7</note> cryings and teares vnto him that was able to helpe him.</p>
            <p>Follow thou then (if thou beeſt a true Chriſtian) that fathers coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, who ſaith vnto thee, <hi>Egrediens domo armet te oratio, &amp; regrediens de platea occurrat oratio.</hi> When thou goeſt out of thy houſe, let prayer arme thee, and when thou returneſt from the ſtreet, let prayer meet thee.</p>
            <p>Now in this good womans pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, you may ſee all thoſe ſix condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions which are neceſſarily requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, in euery true chriſtian prayer. As firſt, that it be faithfull; ſecondly, feruent; thirdly, diſcreet; forthly, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable; fiftly, humble; laſtly with an importunate perſeuerance in the acknowledging our owne miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and giuing to God onely and his glory the hope of our helpe; yet neither preſcribing the means how, nor appoynting him the time when to deliuer vs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:2678:25"/> Orderly theſe words may bee branched into theſe three poyntes:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the firſt noteth for what ſhee pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeth namely mercie, <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue mercie.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond, for whom ſhe prayeth, to wit, her ſelfe, <hi>vpon me.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third, to whom ſhe prayeth, that is to god. <hi>O Lord thou Sonne of Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, It is worth the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king how the Saints of God, the cleerer they haue ſeene into them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, the more vehemently in their moſt piercing prayers haue they cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out for mercie. So the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Dauid</hi> in his booke of <hi>Pſalms</hi> do teſtifie, as in the ſixt Pſalme, where he deſireth God to haue mercie vpon him, becauſe he was weake, and his bones were vexed. <note place="margin">Pſalme 32</note> In an other Pſalme, he entreateth mercie, becauſe he was in trouble, <note place="margin">Pſal. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and his eies, his ſoule, and his belly, were conſumed with griefe. In an other, he craueth mercie, becauſe man goeth about to ſwallowe him
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2678:26"/> vp, and fighteth againſt him conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually.</p>
            <p>Marke ye not how <hi>Manaſſes</hi> in <note place="margin">2. Chron. 34.</note> the dungeon crieth for mercie. <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> in the belly of the whale remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth <note place="margin">Ionas
2.</note> the Lord his God of his old mercies. And the <hi>Publican</hi> in the <note place="margin">Luke 15. 13.</note> Goſpell, with his eies in his hart ſaith, God be mercifull to mee a ſinner.</p>
            <p>This is therefore the baſis, the burthen of all their petitions in the middeſt of their miſeries, Mercie good Lord, mercy we aske, this is the totall ſumme; for mercy Lorde is all our ſute, Lorde let thy mercie come.</p>
            <p>I cannot then ſufficiently woon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at their madneſſe, who forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their owne miſeries, cry out in their prayers for the reward of their merite.</p>
            <p>Surely, theſe men, for lying va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, haue forſaken their owne mercy, yea they haue forſaken God
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2678:26"/> himſelfe, which is made of mercie, and compounded of compaſſion; who, as a father pittieth his owne children, ſo dooth the Lord powre out the bowelles of his compaſſion vpon all them that cry vnto him for it, ſeeking and ſighing for it moſt feruently,</p>
            <p>Heere wee ſee this good woman ſetteth mercy before God. <hi>Haue mercy vpon me O God.</hi> For our God is alway formoſt in mercie, and he neuer ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth, vntill he be hated. As a father ſaieth, <hi>derelinquunt homines Deum, non derelinquunt ur à Deo:</hi> Men leaue God, but they are not left nor forſaken of God: for his mercie is ouer all his workes.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe, that wee may not fall into <hi>Origens</hi> old hereſie, who, to magnifie the mercies of God, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed at the day of iudgement, that all men ſhould be ſaued, as ſome prophane Proteſtants are of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they which haue been once
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2678:27"/> baptized, ſhall neuer be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>To meete with theſe men, let vs learne for a trueth, to whome the mercies of God do properly apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: with thee there is mercie, (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) that thou mayeſt
<note place="margin">Pſalm 130. 4</note> be feared. And his mercie (ſingeth the bleſſed Virgin) is on them that <note place="margin">Luke 1. 50.</note> feare him throughout all generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</p>
            <p>But who is hee that feareth God aright: ſurely, ſaieth <hi>Salomon,</hi> the
<note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou. 9.</note> feare of the Lorde withdraweth, or with-holdeth man from euill. And againe, the feare of the Lorde is the beginning of his loue: for there is no true loue (ſuch as is the inferiour vnto his gratious ſuperior) without ſome feare.</p>
            <p>He therfore that feareth the loſſe of the loue of God, and ſo loueth him that he feareth his diſpleaſure, vnto him appertayneth the mercie of our God for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:2678:27"/> The ſecond braunch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed is, for whome ſhee prayed: to wit, for her ſelfe, <hi>Haue mercie on me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this poynt, theſe foure poynts may be obſerued. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, in that ſhe prayeth for her ſelfe, in her ſelfe fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the afflictions of her daughter: therein wee note the ſimpathie, and mutuall compunction that is to bee found among all the Saints of God: For as in our naturall bodies, if one of the leaſt members be grieued, the whol quiet eſtate of the body is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted with the ſame: ſo is it in the ſpirituall body of the Saintes, like
<hi>Hippocrates</hi> twinnes, they weepe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and they laugh together.</p>
            <p>Therefore, when <hi>Hester</hi> the <note place="margin">Heſter
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Queene faſted and wept,
<hi>Mardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus</hi> with all the Iewes mourned together with her.</p>
            <p>And when our Sauiour behelde how <hi>Mary,</hi> and the Iewes bewayled <note place="margin">Iohn
11. 35</note> the death of <hi>Lazarus:</hi> hee wept alſo
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2678:28"/> with them for company.</p>
            <p>Hence ſayth ſaint <hi>Paule,</hi> who is <note place="margin">2. Cor. 29.</note> weake, and I am not infirme? who weepeth, and I mourne not?</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, whoſoeuer greeueth for himſelfe onelie, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any further touch or inward feeling, of the generall afflictions of the ſaints, his (though a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an affection) may be turned into ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, in that ſhe prayeth for her ſelfe, and in her ſelfe includeth her daughter, the neare and deare collop of her ſelfe, her daughter tormented at home, ſhe abroad, ſeeing and feeling the torture ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. As if ſhe had ſaid, haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie on me, and thou ſhalt extend thy kindnes on my daughter, help me, and ſuccour her, eaſe me, and thou comforteſt her, haue mercie on me, and thou ſhalt be mercifull vnto two; a miſerable mother, and a tormented daughter. Here then
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2678:28"/> we ſee the motherlie affections of a tender hart, which maketh her childes afflictions her owne miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
            <p>Comfortably beyond all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion <note place="margin">Eſay 49. 15</note> ſpeaketh the Lord by his Prophet. Can a mother forget the child of her wombe? could the true harted mother endure before <note place="margin">1. Reg. 3. 26</note> her face the ſlaughter of her owne infant?</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, ſo ſhould all pityfull parents, when they behold their tender yong ones plunged in any ſtraunge ſtriuing pangs, crie out with <hi>Dauid,</hi> haue mercie on me ô Lord, it is I that haue ſinned, for <note place="margin">2. Samu. 12</note> what hath this child done?</p>
            <p>Thus the Lord beateth the dog before the lyon, the lambe before the damme, to tame &amp; bring down thy ſtonie ſtubborne hart.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdlie, in that ſhe ſaith, <hi>Haue mercie on me,</hi> ſhe bewrayeth the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of true compaſſion, which as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2678:29"/> a Father ſaith, <hi>Est vitijs alienis tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulari non implicari, moerere, non he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere, dolore contrahi, non attrahi,</hi> To be troubled with other mens ſinnes, not to bee tainted with them, to groan at them, not to grow in them, to greeue for them, but not to be drawne into them.</p>
            <p>But in truth verie ſoothlie ſaith <hi>Barnard, Impoſſible est ei afflictioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus afflictorum contristari, qui experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum afflictionis in ſe nunquam ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit,</hi> It is not poſſible for him to be greeued at the afflictions of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, who neuer had experience of affliction in himſelfe: for true compaſſion is a Godly affection of pittie, both towardes himſelfe and other: for this cauſe did the high Prieſt, firſt offer ſacrifice for himſelfe, and then for other. And the Preacher counſailes thee, <hi>Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere animae tuae placens Deo,</hi> Pitie thou firſt thine owne ſoule, for that is well pleaſing vnto God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:2678:29"/> Indeed the Phariſie in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, <note place="margin">Luke 18.</note> he was ſorie for the Publican, but the poore Publican was moſt ſorowfull for himſelfe And ſo was <hi>Saul</hi> pittifully minded toward <hi>Agag,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Samu. 15</note> but he had forgotten to be compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate towards his owne ſoule. Marke ye not how the cocke firſt claps his winges againſt his owne ſide, and ſo rowzing vp his hart croweth. And the Lord by his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſpirit ſaith, <hi>Exias á te peccatrix</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ierem.
27.</note> 
               <hi>Babilon,</hi> Come out of thy ſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with thy ſelfe, thou ſinful ſoule of confuſion: Remember thy ſelfe, care for thine owne cure, recouer thine owne health, and then go and ſtrengthen thy brethren.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Athenians</hi> had a cuſtome to ſacrifice vnto their owne gods onelie, for themſelues, and their neighbours: So learne thou, firſt to ſacrifice vnto God, the calues of thine owne lips, with the ſmokie ſighes of a groaning hart, greeued
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2678:30"/> for the ſinnes of thine owne ſoule, be mindfull of thine owne miſeries, and crie for mercie: firſt for thy ſelfe, and then for thy people.</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, he that with <note place="margin">2. Reg. 5</note> 
               <hi>Nahaman</hi> at the commaundement of the Prophet, ſowſeth not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſeauen times a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y in the ſalt ſea ſorrowes of his owne ſoule, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the filthines of his owne fleſh, he ſhall neuer be truelie clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the loathſome leproſie of all his ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Laſtlie, in that ſhe ſaith, <hi>Haue mercie on me,</hi> herein we ſee the three-fold effect of an excellent faith.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is, to remember the ſweet promiſes of mercie. I haue read of many men of wonderfull memories: as <hi>Themistocles, Qui om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uium nomina tenebat,</hi> Who remembred the names of all his Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens. Alſo
<hi>Cyneas,</hi> who in one day had learned to ſalute all the Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2678:30"/> of <hi>Rome,</hi> euery man by his owne name. And of <hi>Lucullus,</hi> whom
<hi>Tully</hi> ſo much commendeth: But there is no obiect more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent for the memorie of man conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallie to beat vpon, then the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable promiſes of Gods eternall mercies.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond effect of faith is, to imbrace (as <hi>Ionathan</hi> did
<hi>Dauid)</hi> the trueth of theſe promiſes, to meet <note place="margin">Iohn 21.</note> them, and greet them (as <hi>Mary</hi> did our Lord Ieſus) betimes in the morning: and to ſalute them by the dawning of the day, and then though ſad ſorrow and heauines hath lodged with vs all night, yet glad, ioy, and cheerfulnes will bring a merrie morrow.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third is to apply theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to thy miſeries, to miniſter this heauenly wholeſome phyſicke to thine owne ſicke ſoule, and to lay theſe cordiall comfortatiues to thy panting and fainting heart, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2678:31"/> ſo ſhalt thou finde reſt, health, and happineſſe for euer.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the flaggons of his <note place="margin">Cantic. 2.</note> pure wine. Theſe are the apples of his deere loue, to reuiue, ſtrengthen, and ſtay thee.</p>
            <p>But alacke for pitty<hi>!</hi> that this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer effect of faith may be ſomtime ſeene, euen among hvpocrites, for <note place="margin">Gene. 27.</note> 
               <hi>Eſau</hi> can remember the benefite of his birth-right, and weepe for it.</p>
            <p>And the ſecond, which is more glorious, is too common vnto Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates, as hee that catcheth hold of a ſlender twine, in hope of help, when hee is ſincking downe to bee drowned.</p>
            <p>Did not the Iewes in the daies of <hi>Ieremy</hi> truſt to the promiſes made to their Temple and Citty of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 19.</note> when the enemy was battring downe their bulwarkes.</p>
            <p>But the third, (which is neuer wrought, but with the finger of Gods owne hand) that is peculiar
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2678:31"/> onely to the elect of God</p>
            <p>This then is our concluſion, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though our Sauiour Chriſt be a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne ſalue, and a moſt pretious plaiſter, able to recure and heale all the feſtred ſoares and foule eating cankars of the ſoule: yet, if thou haſt not this inſtrumentall hand of faith, wherewith thou mayeſt apply this medicine vnto thine owne woundes, powring this oyle and wine, like the wiſe Samaritan, into <note place="margin">Luke 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> euery place, that is periſhed within thee, without all doubt thou ſhalt neuer be ſoundly recouered of thy deadly diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Now to draw to the third branch and laſt member; namely, to whom ſhe prayed, noted in theſe wordes, <hi>O Lord, thou Sonne of Dauid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this poynt let vs followe theſe inſtructions. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, beholde howe this good woman, although her deere daughter was extreamely tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented of the dinell, yet ſhee vſeth
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2678:32"/> not damnable diuelliſh meanes for her eaſe and recouery, ſhe conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not with a coniurer, ſhee whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth not with Witches, with one naile to driue out an other, as with one diuell to caſt out an other, but ſhe directly comes, cries, and calles vpon Chriſt Ieſus for her ſuccour.</p>
            <p>And is not this meere madneſſe when the God of heauen and earth our Father, (a name of fauour) wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <note place="margin">Pſalme 50</note> vs to call vpon him, to ſeeke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, in the time of our trouble, promiſing that he will heare vs, and not that only, but he will deliuer vs, that we may glorifie him, <hi>&amp; nos in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſati,</hi> and wee fooles call vppon his and our enemy: who doth, not onely, not regarde vs, but neuer can deliuer vs: Is not this to run round about in a maze, to be deliuered out of an amazement?</p>
            <p>Beſides this foppery, I would gladly learne of theſe men, what help, or ſound hope of help can any
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2678:32"/> Chriſtian expect from the diuell, or from him that maketh conuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the Diuell for him: ſurely <note place="margin">Auguſt. 3. trinit.</note> their power failed them euen vpon ſlies, and they could not enter into the Swine without permiſſion.
<note place="margin">Mark. 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Beloued, a learned late writer <note place="margin">Hyporius.</note> prooueth by three notable argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (as me ſeemeth) that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſeeketh, either by calculation, or by any Magicall ſtipulation to be relieued in his troubles, he is vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly fallen away from the faith of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is, becauſe he ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth either the abilitie, or the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingnes of God towards him, and to make the leaſt doubt hereof to bring it once into queſtion, is to fall away from our holie faith.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> His ſecond reaſon is, becauſe they commit Idolatrie, and he proueth this, for whoſoeuer craueth or ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for any ſuccour in his neceſſitie of any creature, but of God onely
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2678:33"/> the chiefe creator, he honoureth and worſhippeth that creature vnto whom he ſo ſeeketh, and this is to commit Idolatry, and conſequently, to fall from our holie faith.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> His third reaſon is drawen from the teſtimonie of the diuell, who is an vnanſwerable witneſſe againſt all their ſoules that haue ſought to him for their ſuccour.</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, in this caſe he that ſeeketh for any ſuccour, and hee that helpeth by any extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie diuelliſh meanes to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour any man in his troubles, they are both flat
<hi>Apostatas</hi> from the ſound faith of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond point to be followed is, that this ſeelie woman, ſo weak by nature, ſo baſe by birth, ſo rude by education, brought vp in the midſt of an Idolatrous genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhould notwithſtanding thus crie out vpon a nature aboue all
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2678:33"/> natures, yea, vppon two natures in one perſon, a perfect God for euer.</p>
            <p>Well ſaid the Oratour, there is no nation ſo barbarous, that is not ſeaſoned with the ſauour of ſome god, this is that <hi>Natura naturans,</hi> nature her ſelfe, which nurtureth and nuzleth vs in this opinion<hi>:</hi> If there were no other helpes to proue the eternall deitie.</p>
            <p>Yet there is a helliſh broode of <hi>Atheists,</hi> proude in their own wits, who ſuffocating all light of nature, light of the creatures, and the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious light of the Scriptures, dare denie the manifeſt incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible maieſtie of our euer-lyuing God.</p>
            <p>Did the <hi>Athenians</hi> baniſh <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoras,</hi> becauſe he ſet out a book, doubting whether there were any Gods, and may any Chriſtian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth honour them that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride the bleſſed Trinitie? Theſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2678:34"/> hell hounds ſhould be anſwered with arguments of bloud, which we dailie pray for. In the meane time curſed be they with the great curſe of death, and may it cleaue to them, and al their fauorites for euer, (if they repent not) that maintaine ſo foule a blaſphemie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third point to be followed is, that this good woman in this her prayer giueth vnto our Lord Ieſus the true titles, both of his Godhead and of his Manhood: for ſhe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth him her Lord, and the ſonne of <hi>Dauid.</hi> In that ſhe acknowledgeth him her Lord, ſhe belieueth his dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And in calling him the ſonne of <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſhe approueth his huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</p>
            <p>This Lord is the gratious begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the defenſing, continuing, and finall ending of all creatures. This Lord hath a name not to be named, a name aboue all names, the Lord ſtrong and mightie, the Lord of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2678:34"/> hoſtes, the Lord our light, and our ſaluation, our glorie, our tower, our refuge, and our protection for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p>And as he is the Lord, euen the the God of our fore-fathers, ſo is he alſo the ſonne of
<hi>Dauid,</hi> a man made of our ſeed, lineally deſcended from the loynes of
<hi>Ieſſe,</hi> a branch of the ſame bough, a twig of the ſame tree: but a righteous, not a rotten branch, and therefore is there more in him then in all the ſonnes of men, the poſteritie of <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, Let vs with both eyes behold faithfullie in all our prayers, theſe two natures in one perſon Chriſt Ieſus, his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; wherin his might, his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, wherin his mercie may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended towards vs, that ſo his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull might, and his might full of mercie, may gratiouſlie accept of our petitions, and gratious requeſts. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="treatise">
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:2678:35"/>
            <head>Tractatus Quartus.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Verſe 22.</bibl>
               <q>My daughter is pitteouſly tormented with a Diuell.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS is the firſt aſſault giuen to this good VVo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Faith, which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in a moſt tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call complaint, euery woorde ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his weight of ſorrow. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee will the deeper looke into the greeuouſneſſe of this temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by theſe foure circumſtaunces conſidered therein.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that her Daughter,</p>
            <p>Secondly, is tormented,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:2678:35"/> Thirdly, pitteouſly, or greeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, by the Diuell.</p>
            <p>In that ſhe complaineth, that her daughter, a colop of her owne fleſh, her deare childe, weake by nature, becauſe a woman, fearefull by kind, becauſe a maide, and as neere to her as the skinne of her browes, becauſe her owne daughter.</p>
            <p>Thus wee might ſtay a while to aggrauate the greeuouſneſſe of this temptation, but it ſeemeth that this woman was no ſooner conuerted to the true religion of the God of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, but the diuell by and by aſſault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth her daughter, ſhee findes him, not onely in her owne houſe, in her owne mind, in her heart, and in her concupiſcence, but in her owne limbes, and in her owne bowelles.</p>
            <p>This was a weary welcom at the firſt vnto this true religion.</p>
            <p>Shee might very well haue ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> either this not to be the true
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2678:36"/> religion of God, which bringeth ſuch a ſowre taſte with it at the firſt relliſh, or elſe God regardeth not them, who in the trueth of his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion worſhip him, becauſe he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth the profeſſors thereof to bee ſo greeuouſly tormented.</p>
            <p>But it is vſuall with the Iſrael of God (no ſooner to ſet forward to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the land of Promiſe, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Gods appoyntment) but they ſhall finde infinite troubles, vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and hinderances in their iorney. Man and the Diuell on euery ſide riſing vp againſt them. For, in this caſe, the Diuel is like a wilde Tygre robbed of her whelpes, raging fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly.</p>
            <p>So we find in the Parable of the <note place="margin">Luk. 11.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> vncleane ſpirit, caſt out of the man, he taketh no reſt, vntill (if it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) he hath made his reentry, that the end of that man may be woorſe than the beginning. And this is that <note place="margin">Math. 10.
34.</note> ſword which our Sauiour ſaith he is
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2678:36"/> come to bring into this world.</p>
            <p>Whileſt <hi>Dauid</hi> is at home with his father, all is wel with him: but when he comes to the battell, and ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when hee ſettes forwarde to fight with <hi>Goliah:</hi> his owne brethren be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <note place="margin">1. Samu. 17</note> his heauie hatefull enemies.</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, happy is hee, who through the greeuouſneſſe of theſe temptations (faſtening vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him whileſt hee is yet but as a greene blade in the firſt ſpring) is not ſo offended heerewith, that hee falleth quite away from the truth of his profeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſuppoſeth this childe to haue beene her onely daughter, and therefore the temptation was ſo much the more greeuous: for, if a man hath but one pretious Iewell which he eſteemeth aboue all his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the world: to looſe that, or to be robbed of it, it were an excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding griefe to him, but to bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed of it by his greateſt enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2678:37"/> who in deſpite of him, makes a ſpoyle of it before his face: this is a moſt intollerable iniury.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Abraham</hi> hath but one <note place="margin">Geneſ. 22.</note> ſonne, the onely hope of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and yet he muſt ſacrifice him, this toucheth to the quick, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth very neare the heart, <hi>vna ſalus victis.</hi> But this womans caſe, by many degrees, is more miſerable then was <hi>Abrahams:</hi> for he hath an other ſonne an <hi>Iſmael:</hi> this hath no childe, but her onely daughter, himſelfe ſacrificeth his childe, The Diuell butchereth her childe.</p>
            <p>He knoweth heerein he pleaſeth God: ſhee knoweth, that neyther God nor Man is pleaſed in this deede. And yet theſe bitter pilles, and vnſauory ſawces, are ſometimes moſt wholeſome for our crazed ſoules. For Phyſitions holde there is no ſurffet more perillous then that which is taken of too much honnie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:2678:37"/> Therefore the dungeon in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Reg.
21.</note> was leſſe daungerous to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes,</hi> then the throne of <hi>Iuda.</hi> And it is good for me ſayth <hi>Dauid,</hi> that I <note place="margin">Pſalme 119</note> haue beene in trouble, for nowe I haue learned to keepe thy law. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mamile wel trode vppon, groweth the thicker: and ſpices well pown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſmel the ſweeter.</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, hard aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is, for the moſt part, more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for the children of God, then faire proſperitie can be.</p>
            <p>The ſecond poynt is, that her daughter is tormented, for ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a childe to haue been poſſeſſed, had beene a grieuous thing, but to be tormented, is moſt wretched.</p>
            <p>The Greeke worde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is very ſignificatiue, not as ſome tranſlate it (but not ſo aptly) <hi>furiata eſt,</hi> but <hi>à daemonio agitatur:</hi> which was indeede
<hi>malum praeter naturam:</hi> for this is ſuch a diſeaſe, <hi>qui phiſicè curari non poteſt,</hi> ſhe was torne, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2678:38"/> and peece-meale perplexed by the diuell, as the good mans ſonne was, whome the diuel, whereſoeuer <note place="margin">Marke 9. 18.</note> he tooke, cauſed him to teare hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to foame at the mouth, gnaſhing his teeth, and pining a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
            <p>Herein we note the furious might of the diuel, for he had a threefolde power ouer this poore maiden. The firſt was to enter into her, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe her: the ſecond was, in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, to torment her: the third was miſerably pitteouſly, and greeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly to do it And this power is gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God, vnto this common en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of mankinde, becauſe of our ſinne: for as wee did willingly and wilfully caſt away our louing obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience vnto God: ſo,
<hi>pari metria,</hi> by the like proportion of iuſtice, it is reaſon that <hi>Saul</hi> rule ouer them <note place="margin">1. Sam. 9.</note> that call for him to be their King.</p>
            <p>And this permitted power of his, hee dooth ſometimes exerciſe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2678:38"/> (but as Gods executioner) euen vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them that are neare and deare vn to their louing and beloued God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which hee dooth eyther inuiſibly in their mindes, or viſibly vppon their bodies.</p>
            <p>In their mindes three manner of wayes, either abuſing their incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulitie, as he did in
<hi>Thomas.</hi> Or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <note place="margin">Iohn 20. 18.</note> in drawing it into deſpayre, as he did in <hi>Cain:</hi> or blinding or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſotting <note place="margin">Geneſ. 4.
3.</note> their vnderſtanding, ſo that they cannot conceiue that they haue heard, and read of heauenly matters, as hee did the Apoſtles, in miſtak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Sauiours ſpeach of
<hi>Leauen:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 12. 6</note> and Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh of many
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3. 16</note> that ſo peruerted S. <hi>Paules</hi> Epiſtles vnto their own perdition: Or third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, confounding their memorie, ſo that they haue quite and cleane for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, what admoniſhment and forewarnings they haue had by the Holy-ghoſt: as the Prophet that had forgotten the commandement <note place="margin">1. Reg. 13.</note>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:2678:39"/> to returne faſting after his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage. And <hi>Peter</hi> had forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<note place="margin">Iohn 13. 38</note> the watch-word of the cocke crow.</p>
            <p>The Diuell doth alſo execute his power ſometime vpon the bodies of the Saints and children of God, viſiblie and ſenſiblie, ſmiting them, as he did that holie man of god <hi>Iob.</hi> Yea, and he feared not to ſet vpon th'immaculate bodie of our Lord <note place="margin">Math 4.
8.</note> Ieſus Chriſt, carrying him from the wildernes to the tops of the high mountaines, and from the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines to the citie, and from the citie to the pinacle of the Temple &amp;c. So that I am eaſilie drawne into this opinion, <hi>Omne ſublu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare,</hi> euerie elementarie bodie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Moone is maruellouſlie captiuated to this permiſſiue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer.</p>
            <p>And this hath our Lord GOD graunted vnto him in his wiſdome; Foure notable reaſons iuſtlie vrg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2678:39"/> him thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, becauſe he doth thus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt vnto the view of all the world, that all the ſort of vs, are guiltie of ſinne, and haue deſerued by our offences, againſt his ſupreme ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, not onelie to be poſſeſſed, but alſo thus to be tormented by the executioner of his will. For as the Lord ſaith to the Prophet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <note place="margin">1. Sam. 9.</note> the houſe of Iſraell, they haue not caſt thee away: but they haue caſt me away, that I ſhould not raigne ouer them: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did he giue them one in his wrath to rule ouer them, and they did feele the ſmart of his tyrannous dominion.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond reaſon is, becauſe hee will by this meanes, openly humble vs, and bring vs downe, bruzing the pride of our hartes, abating and abaſhing the mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious imaginations of our high mindes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:2678:40"/> Thus did he hamper and throw downe the mightie Monarche of <hi>Babilon, Nabuchadnezar.</hi> And thus <note place="margin">Dan. 9.</note> did he bring him to the knowledge of him ſelfe to ſit at Ieſus feet that was poſſeſſed with the Legion. <note place="margin">Marke 8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third reaſon is, that thus he might make all the endes of the world to feare him, and to walke before him in a reuerent regard of his diuine power, in holines and righteouſnes all the dayes of their life. For as yong <hi>Tobias,</hi> when he <note place="margin">Tob. 7.</note> vnderſtood that ſeauen of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſours had been ſucceſſiuelie ſtrangled in their wedding bed, therfore did he with the more duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deuotion by his holie prayers ſanctifie the ſame, wherby the feind fayled in his force, and was put to ſlight. So, whoſoeuer he is that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the rule of the Goſpell, to watch and pray leaſt he fall into temptation, he ſhal eſcape the ſnares of this great hunter, and the grins
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2678:40"/> of this crafty fowler, ſo that they ſhall not faſten vppon him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth reaſon is, that thus the Lord openly executing his fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iudgements, all the Atheiſts and profane Epicures of the earth, may knowe themſelues to be but menne, and whatſoeuer may befall a man, that alſo may faſten and light vpon them: for as they palpablie ſee ſuch a one, who is very lamentably tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, not with any naturall mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady, whereof there may be giuen a reaſon &amp; a remedy by phiſick, vnto the party ſo perplexed for his eaſe, but extraordinarily by ſom ſupreme power furiouſly oppreſſed: ſo may they bee enforced to confeſſe, the ſame danger is neere vnto them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, for they are of the ſame mettall and moulde, of the ſame forme and faſhion like vnto other men. For the Diuel feared not <hi>Saul,</hi> becauſe he was a King, for to the mightie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine mighty puniſhments. And
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2678:41"/> if there were no other reaſon, mee thinkes this might ſerue to conuince their conſciences, in the confeſſing of God, becauſe, by their experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence they haue found there is a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, the executioner of miſchiefe vpon the ſonnes of men. Doubtles then there is his contrary, who is God, ſhewing mercy and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion towards them that feare him.</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, Be the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and might of the Diuell neuer ſo extreame, and his tortures neuer ſo intollerable, yet whoſoeuer hee is, that abideth in the ſhaddowe of the Almightie, hee that hath made the Lord his hope, his fortreſſe, and his truſt, he ſhalbe deliuered from this noyſome euill. The Lord ſhall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him vnder his wings, &amp; he ſhall
<note place="margin">Pſal. 81.</note> be ſure vnder his feathers, his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and trueth ſhalbe his ſhield and buckler, ſo that he ſhall not be afraide of the feare of the night, nor of the arrow that flieth by day, hee
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2678:41"/> ſhal cal vpon the name of the Lord, and hee will heare him, hee will be with him in his troubles, to deliuer and glorifie him for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third poynt is, that her daughter is pitteouſly tormented, had ſhee beene quietly poſſeſſed, or lightly tormented, for a twitch and away, it had beene the more tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, but herein appeareth the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of the enemy, that hee dooth ſo greeuouſly and ſo outragiouſly tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo ſeely and ſo ſimple a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>Eraſmus</hi> (me thinketh) dooth fitly terme it <hi>Miſerè,</hi> howſoeuer the Greeke word is
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: but more ſignificatiuely is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is ſo pitiouſly that it would pity any ones hart to ſee her torments<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> much more rent the mothers heart. But her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>by we note, that ſome the Diuell poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth, and doth not torment, and ſome he poſſeſſeth and tormenteth pitteouſly. Hee poſſeſſed and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented not <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> thogh
<note place="margin">Luke 7. 37.</note>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:2678:42"/> we reade there were ſeauen diuelles in her: but he poſſeſſed, and very often greeuouſly tormented <hi>Saul.</hi> Hee poſſeſſed, but tormented not
<note place="margin">Acts 19. 16.</note> him that ranne vpon the ſeuen ſons of <hi>Sceua</hi> the Iew, and wounded them: Euen ſo he poſſeſſeth many in theſe dayes, the children of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, that liue according to the courſe of this worlde, but hee ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not ſo greeuouſlie to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment them; for what may wee thinke elſe of them, in whom the ſeauen deadly damnable ſinnes rule and raigne, hath not Sathan erected his throne in their dwellings, and are they not poſſeſſed of him? What can ye imagine when ye beholde a painted faced wanton, ſet out with her ſtrange tinckling head tire, her curled perwigges, her coſtly glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering apparell, her fan, her maske, her bracelet, her necklace, her rings, her chaines, her muffe, her ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, her fine ſtarched linnen, her
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2678:42"/> out-ſtretched necke, her bare naked breaſtes, her wandering eyes, her mincing gate, with her tinckling ſlippers? Can ye ſay otherwiſe then that there is a puppet poſſeſſed (yea and after a ſorte) tormented with a prowde diuell? And ſo wee may affirme of all the reſt, as of enuy and malice, whooredome and adultery, couetouſnes and gluttony, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, whenſoeuer the ennemy to our ſaluation dooth dangerouſly poſſeſſe, he would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo greeuouſly torment that partie, but that he is for a while reſtrained by the imperiall power of powers. And therefore lette vs be ſober and
<note place="margin">1. Peter 5. 8.</note> watch, becauſe our aduerſary the diuell goeth about as a roaring lion, ſeeking whome hee may deuoure. Euery woorde in the Apoſtles rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is full of force: As firſt, becauſe he is our aduerſary; ſecondly, he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth about, hee laboureth and plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vnceſſantly; thirdly, like a roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2678:43"/> lion, full of might and malice; fourthly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſeeking, ſearching, and winding out in his ſubtiltie; laſtly, whomeſoeuer, rich or poore, high or low, he may deuoure, not onely poſſeſſe and torment in this life, but the miſeries of this vile life beeing come to an end, hee may ſwallowe vp into euerlaſting perdition with himſelfe for euer, whome reſiſt you (beloued) in your ſtrong faith, and hee ſhall flee from you.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt poynt is, by whome her daughter was thus pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly tormented, namely, by the diuell: if ſhee had beene tormented by ſome extraordinary ſickeneſſe, it had beene greeuous; or tormented by ſome vnnaturall mercileſſe men, (the more to be pittied) but to bee tormented of the Diuell, the ſworne ennemy vnto all mankind, one that will not bee ſatisfied with the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this life, bee they neuer ſo many, nor miſerable: this is as heauy,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2678:43"/> as wofull, and as greeuous a caſe as euer was heard of: but heerein we are giuen to note theſe two things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is, the crauen coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines in this fowle enemy, in that he tyrannizeth ouer ſo poore a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo weake a childe. Indeed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and
<hi>Adam,</hi> in the glory of <note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.</note> his creation there was ſome equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and betwixt him, and our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <note place="margin">Mat. 4.</note> Chriſt, ſome match: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him, and this weake child, this ſeely gerle, <hi>impar congreſſus,</hi> there was great oddes in the conflict.</p>
            <p>This hath beene his cuſtome of olde, to ſet vpon the weakeſt, and therefore he firſt aſſaulted the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.</note> whome hee knew to bee the weaker veſſell, that for the loue of her, the man might the rather bee drawne into diſobedience. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he aſſaulteth both the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Lot,</hi> that they might the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier intice <note place="margin">Geneſ. 19</note> their father vnto ſinne. So when he had leaue to combate with
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2678:44"/> 
               <hi>Iob,</hi> he firſt layes his battery againſt his goodes, then vpon his children, and laſtly, on his wife, that he might thus haue preuailed againſt that good man. And (beloued) doe yee not marke, that this is ordinary in the diuels darlings, and their world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dealings? Doe they not vſually force the weakeſt to the wall: ſo that they which worſt may, muſt holde the candle.</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, The Saintes <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 37.</note> of God in all theſe things are more then conquerors, through him that loueth them; for in their weakenes, his ſtrength, and in their infirmities, his power is manifeſted to his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall glory.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond thing to be noted, is, that which Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, Let no <note place="margin">Iam. 1. 13.</note> man ſay when he is tempted, I am tempted of God: for God can not be tempted with euil, neither temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth he any man, but euery man is tempted when hee is drawne away
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2678:44"/> by his owne concupiſcence, and is enticed: fitly therefore doe the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers define a temptation to bee a corrupt affection, tending or enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing vnto euill, and to imagine this to come neere to God is high blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy. The matter therefore of our temptation is in vs, euen our owne concupiſcence, the diuil nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth but to bring his bellowes vnto this fire, and it is foorthwith kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
            <p>We may reade indeede that God prooueth vs, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſayeth vnto <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 20.</note> the people, feare not, your God is come to prooue you: and ſo the Pſalmiſt ſingeth, thou (O GOD) <note place="margin">Pſalme 66. 10</note> haſt prooued vs, thou haſt tried vs, as ſiluer is tried. Hence is it that we ſay Gods trialles are like vnto the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners worke, vppon the ſiluer and golde, the droſſe is conſumed, but the mettall is the purer. On the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, the Diuelles temptations are like vnto <hi>Sampſons</hi> foxes, burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Iudg. 15.</note>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:2678:45"/> the good corne, and leauing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the ſtubble, and aſhes. Gods trialls, they alway tend to his glory, and our good. But the diuels temptations, they will alway runne to his reioycing, and our ſhame.</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, God is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 13</note> who will not lay vppon his Saintes aboue that they are able to beare, but will giue the iſſue with the temptation, to his glory, and our eternall comfort.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, ſince wee ſee howe daungerous a thing it is to haue the diuell domeſticall at home with vs, eyther in our ſelues, or in our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or in any of our family.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore, by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this good woman, lay open our ſinnes (whereby wee are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed, though wee be not ſenſibly tormented by the Diuell) vnto our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie hee may pardon that is paſt, and hereafter, in that which is to come,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2678:45"/> albeit ſinne can not cleane bee caſt out of vs, yet the power thereof may bee deiected in vs, that wee may die vnto ſinne, and liue vnto righteouſneſſe and holineſſe for euer, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="treatise">
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:2678:46"/>
            <head>Tractatus quintus</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Verſe 23.</bibl>
               <q>But he anſwered her not a word.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe words we are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to this good womans faith, the greeuouſnes whereof may be the cleerer ſeen into, if we can but conſider a while with our ſelues, what a diſmaie, and a diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (ouer and aboue the inraging griefe thereof) it ſtriketh into the hart of any ſuter, to make his moane
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2678:46"/> and humble petition vnto him, that neither heareth nor regardeth him: for who can endure ſtill to intreat him, whom he findeth inexorable, or perſeuer to call vpon him who is wilfully deafe and dumbe. Indeed <hi>Elias</hi> worthelie laughed at <hi>Baals</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Reg. 18. 17</note> prieſtes ſtabbing them ſelues and crying out vnto that which was but an Idoll (that is the worke of mans handes) which hath eares but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not heare, eyes and cannot ſee &amp;c. But it will make any man roare out in the horrour of his hart, when he hath vnceſſantlie called vpon his omniſcient God, and can not be harkened vnto.</p>
            <p>This makes the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 13.</note> with ſuch vehemencie to expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late with God, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſque quo Domine?</hi> How long ô Lord wilt thou forget me, for euer? how long ſhall I crie vnto thee? how long wilt thou hide thy face from me, and how long ſhall I be wearied in my hart? In
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2678:47"/> ſuch a caſe, or far more grieuous was this good womans at this time, which that it may be the better exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, we will branch forth this temptation into her three fold aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults, drawen from the wordes as they lie before vs.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is, that our Sauiour Chriſt doth not anſwere.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond, that he doth not anſwere her, euen her that crieth out ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third, that hee doth not vouchſafe to anſwere her one word. And of theſe orderlie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[But he anſwered her not a word,]</hi> The firſt word in theſe words ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauateth the acrimonie and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of this temptation, for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt ſeemeth to inferre that this womans outcrie was verie patheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and full of moouing, but Ieſus Chriſt for all that ſeemeth to be no more touched therwith, then the deep rooted oke is, with the blaſt of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2678:47"/> euery litle gale.</p>
            <p>It is ſtrange, and ſurpaſſeth the amazement of reaſon, that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt ſhould giue out ſuch kind commaundements, and annex therunto ſuch large promiſes as theſe: Aske largelie: Open thy mouth wide, and I wil fill it. Again, <note place="margin">Pſalme
81.</note> Aske and it ſhal be giuen you. And again, Whatſoeuer ye aske the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<note place="margin">Matth. 7. 7</note> in my name<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he ſhall giue you, and ſuch like, infinite. And now when a ſilly needie weak woman asketh ſeeketh, knocketh, and crieth out aloude, he is as one dumbe and tongue tyed.</p>
            <p>There are three ſorts of anſwers which in the common ciuilitie of manners are vſuallie ſhaped. The firſt is of neceſſitie: the ſecond of humanitie: and the third of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluitie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is made when an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere is extreamly vrged.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond is when it is curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2678:48"/> demanded.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third is full of tedious yrke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomnes, knowing no end of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</p>
            <p>Our Sauiour Chriſt in this place is both vrged, and mournfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted, and yet he frameth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe anſweres vnto her.</p>
            <p>Queſtionles, our Lord Ieſus Chriſt will ſometime ſeeme to his Saints in the afflictions of their ſoules, as one deafe and dumbe, not daining to anſwere them. So ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med he to that holie man <hi>Iob,</hi> as <note place="margin">Iob. 10. 20.</note> himſelf teſtifieth: When I crie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, thou heareſt not, neither regardeſt thou me when I ſtand vp. And the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, I haue cried vnto thee in the
<note place="margin">Pſal. 22.</note> day time, and thou heareſt not, and in the night ſeaſon, and thou regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt me not<hi>:</hi> ſo that, day and night, and night and day, he that created the eare, he doth not heare, and he that ſaid, Call vpon me in the time
<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.</note>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:2678:48"/> of thy trouble, and I will heare thee, and deliuer thee, that thou maieſt glorifie me. Yet euen he I ſay ſome times ſeemeth not ro reſpect the requeſts and queſts of our groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings.</p>
            <p>And this is done, not becauſe he cannot, or becauſe he wil not ſpeak: but there are foure deuine reaſons in his heauenly wiſdome that lead him therunto.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe the vehemencie of our longing deſire, by this forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſhould be the more incenſed: for a ioy deferred though for a time, <note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> it breedeth the fainting of the ſoule, yet when it comes, it is a tree of life. So vſe our Smithes to throw water vpon their burning forge, that by the blaſtes of the bellowes, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed fire may rage the hotter. And thus the Lord ſeemed not to regard thoſe outcries, which the people threw vp into the heauens, when they were in that extreame
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2678:49"/> exigent vpon the bankes of the red ſea ſhore, that their miraculous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance might be celebrated with the greater triumph.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond reaſon is, becauſe the benefit which is with many cries, &amp; much ſweating obtaind, is the higher eſteemed: for that prouerb holdeth true; Eaſie got, is ſoone forgot.</p>
            <p>This maketh the hauen ſo wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to the ſea-faring man, who hath been deeplie endangered with many a tempeſtuous ſtorme. And this made the day of <hi>Dauids</hi> coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and eſtabliſhment in the throne of Iſraell ſo triumphant, when through ſo many croſſes and calamities, at the laſt he came to it: So is peace the ſweeter after warre; and pining hunger maketh homely fare verie toothſome.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third reaſon is, becauſe our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt wil thus mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly conuince the ſtubborne fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward harted Iewes, whom he par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doneth
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:2678:49"/> blaſpheming him, whom he ſatisfieth tempting him, and vnto whom he ſingeth ſweetly, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſtopped vp their eares againſt him.</p>
            <p>Here they ſee him not anſwering her that cries out vnto him for help, &amp; there ſhe ſeeth them not anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him that night &amp; day ſtretcheth out his hand to embrace them, and lifteth vp his voice like a Trumpet, ſounding vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wil not hear him. So ſhal
<hi>Sodom</hi> condemne <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Tirus</hi> and <hi>Sidon</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the pride of <hi>Capernaum</hi> in the reuealing day of Gods Iuſtice. And ſo (I feare) the religious deuotion of our ignorant Papiſts, will conuince vs of ſtonie coldnes towardes the truth of our Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth and laſt reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt thus teacheth vs, that in many caſes hee will not heare, not anſwere vs, but at the importunate ſutes of our inceſſant prayers, for ſo he
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:2678:50"/> ſignifieth vnto vs by that parable of that vnrighteous Iudge, who nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<note place="margin">Luke 18. 2.</note> feared God, nor regarded man: for thus he concludeth, ſhall not God heare his elect which crie night and day vnto him, though he ſuffer long; I tell you he will heare &amp; reuenge them, and that quickly.</p>
            <p>Some diuels will not be caſt out, but with long faſting and many <note place="margin">Mark
7.</note> prayers, and ſome thinges may not be graunted at the firſt hand. Mark ye not how
<hi>Abraham</hi> itterateth his <note place="margin">Geneſ. 18.</note> prayers for the interceſſion of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> And <hi>Elias</hi> muſt pray ſeauen <note place="margin">1. Reg. 18.</note> times before he obtayneth raine in the dayes of <hi>Ahab.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, as the Lord ſaid to his Prophet, whether they heare, or heare not, ſonne of man, ſpeake thou. So ſay I to you, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he anſwere, or anſwere not, yet let not vs deſiſt from our cries, let vs not giue ouer to call vpon him: for though he anſwere not, yet he
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:2678:50"/> heareth, and in hearing he concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the neceſſitie of our requeſts.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond point to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in this aſſault giuen to this good womans faith, is, that he anſwereth not her, who cries out to him for an anſwere, not her that wearieth him and his company with her clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous noyſe, and purſueth him with a moſt pitifull petition.</p>
            <p>Was it not a generall proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion publiſhed vnto all Nations without acceptance of perſons by the Prophet, Whoſoeuer calleth <note place="margin">Ioel 2.</note> vpon the name of the Lord ſhall be ſaued? This woman had heard therof, and ſhe faſtneth the ſhoote-anker of her faith vpon this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and hereupon ſhe is bold to crie and call, but he anſwereth her not a word.</p>
            <p>Marke ye not how he offereth his ſuccouring helpe to vs that ſought <note place="margin">Gen.
3.</note> it not, and calls vpon vs for an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that would not willinglie
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2678:51"/> haue heard him. Yea he continueth his heauenly talke with her, that wrangled with him at <hi>Iacobs</hi> well: <note place="margin">Iohn 4.</note> but heere, to a poore, carefull, and comfortleſſe creature, vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly calling vpon him for it, he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth her not a word.</p>
            <p>Indeede the Prophet proteſteth <note place="margin">Ezech 11.</note> in the name of the Lord, ſaying, are ye come to crie after me? As I liue, ſaith the Lorde, I will not anſwere you. But this was ſpoken to a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that had deſpiſed his callings, and regarded not his admonitions. So ſaith he by the Kingly Prophet: The wicked ſhall cry, yea euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<note place="margin">Pſal 18.</note> the Lord, but hee ſhall not heare them.</p>
            <p>But in another place hee ſingeth, The Lord hath looked down from his ſanctuary, out of his holy heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hath hee behelde the earth, that hee might heare the mournings of the priſoner, and deliuer the children appoynted vnto death. <note place="margin">Pſalme 102</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:2678:51"/> When <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> ſawe <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mias</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Nehem.
1.</note> in the ſorrow of his heart, with a ſad countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hanging his head, he prouoked him to ſpeake and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray the griefes of his minde, and he anſwered him kingly and kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to his hearts liking. So the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <note place="margin">Ierem. 38.</note> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had taken vp a prouerb in the dayes of <hi>Ieremy,</hi> The King can deny vs nothing: but this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb ſeemeth now to be inuerted; for this bounteous King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> will graunt vs nothing, no not ſo much as an anſwer of one word.</p>
            <p>Heereby wee are giuen to learne two leſſons: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that in all the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions of our harts we remember to giue God this honor, that he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth when it is fitteſt, both for vs to be heard, and for him to anſwer vs.</p>
            <p>This had the prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well practized, as himſelfe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth,
<hi>Expectans expectaui Dominum,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſalme 40.</note> I waited long, and ſought the Lord, and patiently did beare. And ſo the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:2678:52"/> Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> teſtifieth, that he <note place="margin">Eſay 28.
16</note> which beleeueth, maketh no haſt: for as faith is not at her firſt concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in her fulnes, neither is her ſtrength, perfected at her firſt birth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond is, that we muſt not therefore onely continue the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of our faithfull prayers, becauſe wee woulde preuayle in our petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but becauſe howſoeuer it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth out with vs. Yet we know this is the iſſue and end of our dooings, that heerein wee haue doone that which was commaunded vs. Wee haue obeyed the will of our GOD, and we haue beene exerciſed in that which hath beene well pleaſing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.</p>
            <p>So then, <hi>ex congruo,</hi> what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde may wee looke for, dooing no more than our neceſſary duetie; or, <hi>ex condigno,</hi> neyther dooing it ſo often, nor ſo well as it ought to be done.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:2678:52"/> Whether then wee be not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered vnto out cries, or if we be ſometime anſwered, as <hi>Salomon</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Reg. 2. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> anſwereth his mother, making an vnaduiſed ſute for his brother
<hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niah,</hi> thou haſt asked this againſt his life, wee are neuertheleſſe to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the practize of our prayers, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the ſucceſſe thereof to his fauour, that both vnderſtandeth them, and what is fitteſt for vs.</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, let vs not bee wearie of well doing; for, how ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they went foorth weeping, in <note place="margin">Pſalme 126</note> bearing of their pretious ſeede, yet they made at the laſt a ioyfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, bringing their ſheaues in their boſome.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third thing to be looked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to in this greeuous aſſault, is, that he aunſwered her not a worde, herein expreſſing the maner of the Iewes behauiour towards the Canaanites, whome, as prophane dogges, they thought not woorthy to be ſpoken vnto.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:2678:53"/> So I read of one <hi>Pallas,</hi> whom the Emperour <hi>Claudius Caeſar</hi> made a free man, who forgetting his owne late ſeruile eſtate, would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vouchſafe to ſpeake to any ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant; but when they mooued any queſtion vnto him, hee aunſwered either by a nodde, or by the poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of his finger; or if the buſines ſo required, by writing; but they coulde neuer wring a worde out of his mouth vnto them.</p>
            <p>Good Lord that the king of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Reg. 6. 27</note> in that extreame famine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called vppon by an vnnaturall mother, for ſome helpe, at the laſt he giueth her this anſwere, ſeeing the Lorde dooth not ſuccour thee how can I helpe thee?</p>
            <p>And yet this our King of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, in whom all health, help and ſuccour is heaped vp, being ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly vrged by ſo faithfull a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, will not vouchſafe her the anſwer of one woord. Doubtleſſe
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:2678:53"/> this temptation was exceeding gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous.</p>
            <p>Had hee ſaide to her but as hee did to blinde <hi>Bartimeus,</hi> What wilt thou that I do to thee? Or as he did <note place="margin">Luke 19.</note> to <hi>Zacheus,</hi> I will to day dine with thee: or but as he ſaid to the Diuell, <note place="margin">Marke 5.</note> Hold thy peace; it had bin ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. But behold, the heauenly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury of eternall happineſſe is cloſe ſhutte vp, and he anſwers her not a worde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter</hi> ſaide very truely of this our ſweet Sauior. Thou haſt the words
<note place="margin">Iohn 6.</note> of eternal life, not only the words of authority to commaunde creation, and the wordes of wiſedome to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and order, but alſo the words of grace and health, to recouer and cure; and the wordes of power to conuert and ſaue, and the words of wonder to confound &amp; deſtroy, and yet at this inſtant he wil not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere with one of all theſe woordes. If it had pleaſed him to deigne her
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:2678:54"/> but that cold anſwere, which <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> ſometime gaue to the poore widdow, who had been a long ſuter in a lawfull cauſe, <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt mihi otium,</hi> As yet I haue no leaſure; yet this might haue breathed ſome hope of help into her hart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an other time, but not to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere her a word, neither good nor bad, not once to open his lips, not to beſtow the eaſie labour of one word vpon her, this pang pincheth paſſing ſore.</p>
            <p>Thus may we reade, that thrice our Sauiour would not vouchſafe the anſwere of one word when it was demaunded of him.</p>
            <p>The firſt was vnto the high <note place="margin">Marke 14. 61</note> Prieſt, and thoſe periured falſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworne witneſſes that agreed not togither againſt him. The Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt ſaith, but he held his peace and anſwered not a word.</p>
            <p>The ſecond was vnto <hi>Herod</hi> &amp; his <note place="margin">Luke 23. 9</note> men of warre, deſpiſing &amp; mocking
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:2678:54"/> him, who although contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly they queſtioned with him of many thinges, but (ſayth the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt) he anſwered nothing.</p>
            <p>The third was vnto <hi>Pilate,</hi> exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining him, when he was accuſed of the chiefe Prieſts and Elders, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vrged to purge himſelfe, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <note place="margin">Math. 27.
14.</note> thou not how many things they lay againſt thee? It followeth, but he anſwered him not one worde, in ſomuch that the Gouernor marue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led greatly. Nowe then, if that rule holde, that
<hi>Omnis Chriſti actio eſt noſtra inſtructio,</hi> then are we learned hereby vnto three kindes of menne, ſometime not to vouchſafe an aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. The firſt are idolatrous prieſts and falſe witneſſes: the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond are diſſolute courtiers and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate ſouldiers: the third are men pleaſing Iudges, and meale-mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>But, to paſſe ouer theſe, as with a finger touched, in this ſilence our
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:2678:55"/> Sauior teacheth vs theſe two things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that there is a ſeaſon of ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, as well as of ſpeach, and he is a perfect wiſe man that knowes and obſerues his due times: for there is more wiſdome ſometime ſeen by ſilence, then learning or diſcretion diſcouered by ſpeaking
<hi>Salomon</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth this to be one of the three things that bewraieth a foole, euen his too much babling. Hence was it that <hi>Socrates</hi> taught his ſchollars to learne a ſeauen yeres ſilence with this experimentall reaſon, <hi>Quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plurimos vidi in grauiſſima incidiſſe peccata loquendo, tacendo nullos,</hi> I haue obſerued many to haue fallen into great offences by ſpeaking, but neuer any by keeping ſilence. The tongue therfore being ſo vnrulie an euill, hath God lockt vp within the two walles of the teeth, and the two barres of the lips. For it is moſt true, <hi>Eſt irreuocabile verbum.</hi> And that father ſaid wiſely, <hi>Paruus ſermo leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:2678:55"/> 
               <hi>volat, ſedgrauiter vulnerat.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Barnard.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid</hi> to ſet a watch before our lips, that we offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not with our ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, that we may learne to ſpeak ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but ſure, &amp; fitly to the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The other thing learned vs, is, that although our Sauiour Chriſt ſpeaketh not outwardly to this good woman, giuing her a verball anſwer, framed of ſillables and wordes, yet inwardly and ſpiritually he ſpeaketh vnto her ſoule two maner of waies. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt, by his holy word, wherin he ſtill remembreth her of his grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promiſes, aſſured to them that call for them, yea, to all ſuch as call for them faithfully: for it is written, He will not deſpiſe the low eſtate of the poore, nor hide himſelfe from him, but when he calleth he will hearken vnto him. So was the word of god the prophet <hi>Dauids</hi> comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">Pſal. 21.</note> &amp; his counſellors, &amp; how ſoeuer after diuers maners god in elder time
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:2678:56"/> ſpake to our fathers by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, yet in theſe laſt dayes he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth <note place="margin">Hebr. 1.</note> thus now to ſpeak vnto vs by his owne ſonne in his moſt holie word. Let vs therefore ſearch the Sciptures, for they teſtifie of him, and in them, and by them he ſtill ſpeaketh comfortably vnto his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly he ſpeaketh vnto this woman by his holy ſpirit, ſealing vp the truth of thoſe his promiſes in her hart, whereby ſhe was confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently perſwaded, that howſoeuer he forbore to open his mouth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her: yet it was impoſſible for him to forget her outcries, or to helpe her.</p>
            <p>Thus ſpake the Lord vnto <hi>Ionas</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ionas
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in the bottome of the ſea, and in the deep darknes of the Whales bellie. And ſo the Lord ſpake vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> mourning like a doue, and bathing himſelfe in his ſalt-brine teares.</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, we haue his
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:2678:56"/> holie word, wherein we heare him ſpeaking vnto vs, and we haue his holie ſpirit, whereby he ſpeaketh within vs: Therefore the Lord will not be ſilent for euer, he hath not forgotten to be mercifull, neither will he ſhut vp his tender mercies in diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>This is our weaknes, to ſuſpect our all-ſeeing, all-hearing, and all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing GOD to bee deafe, or dumbe. Surely, though wee be poore and needy, our GOD think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpon vs, he will anſwere, and will helpe vs. O Lord make no long tarry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="treatise">
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:2678:57"/>
            <head>Tractatus Sextus.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Verſe 24.</bibl>
               <q>Then came his Diſciples and beſought him, ſaying, ſend her away, for ſhe crieth after vs.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E are now lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched into the maine ſtreame of this hyſtorie, wherein we find the Diſciples of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt will haue their oare, they will ſtrike their ſtroke, they will be actors and dealers heerein; who not vnderſtanding their Lordes ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret intendement, think it an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent and a ſhameles part in them to ſuffer this wofull woman ceaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:2678:57"/> thus to follow them, crying ſtill out, and bawling after them, and therefore they are now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſuters in her behalfe, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him to ſend her away. But that which diſquieted them, reioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced our Lord Ieſus, for their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentment in this caſe, pleaſeth our ſweet Sauiour.</p>
            <p>We wil at this time, through the aſſiſtance of Gods holie ſpirit, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute theſe wordes as they lie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, drawne into this order.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In the firſt place we will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue who they be that make this petition in the behalfe of this care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full crying woman, noted in theſe wordes, <hi>Then came his Diſciples and beſought him &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond is the ſumme of this their requeſt in theſe wordes,
<hi>Send her away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third is the reaſon rendred of this their requeſt in theſe wordes,
<hi>for ſhe crieth after vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:2678:58"/> 
               <hi>Then came his Diſciples,]</hi> By this comming of the Diſciples vnto our Lord Ieſus, this ſilly <hi>Syropheniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> might begin to conceaue ſome comfort, for thus might ſhe argue within her ſelfe; He hath not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered me one word; I graunt it, for I am vnworthy to haue that bliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full gratious mouth opened vnto me. But now that I heare his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples haue made a motion for me, they are ſuch as are neare and deare to him, whom he vſeth in moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar kindnes, ſurelie their Lord can deny them nothing: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſince it hath pleaſed them to ſolicite him in my behalfe, I am in good hope to preuaile with him: For indeed this hath been a court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like practiſe in the traffike of this world, according to the French prouerbe:</p>
            <q>
               <l>He that will the French King win,</l>
               <l>With his fauorites he muſt begin.</l>
            </q>
            <p>So we reade, when <hi>Abſalom</hi> labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:2678:58"/> to recouer his fathers princelie fauour, and had procured <hi>Ioab</hi> to further it, when he perceiued that <hi>Ioab</hi> went but ſlowly about it, mark
<note place="margin">2. Sam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 14</note> I pray you to prick him forward, what a pranck he played him.</p>
            <p>So when <hi>Mardocheus</hi> warelie <note place="margin">Heſter 15</note> watched for an opportune acceſſe into the kings preſence, which for him ſelfe raſhly to haue dared to do, was the danger of his head<hi>:</hi> for this was the <hi>Perſian</hi> law, whoſoeuer comes into the inner court of the kings Pallace vncalled, ſhall die the death, vnleſſe the king hold forth his golden Rod vnto him, therfore doth <hi>Mardocheus</hi> wiſelie herein vſe
<hi>Hester</hi> the Queenes good helpe, as a gratious meanes for him. Princes pallaces, and rich mens houſes haue great gates, large courtes, and many a winding roome, ſo that the out cries of the poore oppreſſed may eaſilie vaniſh in the emptie aire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can pierce into their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:2678:59"/> Parlours: I haue heard a reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and learned Lawyer of this land proteſt once, with great vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie, he could ſaile into <hi>France,</hi> trauell into <hi>Paris,</hi> and make his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, better cheape, then hee was able to paſſe through the Lorde Chancelors great chamber, to come to priuate ſpeech with him. Hence is it that wee vſurpe that olde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe,</p>
            <q>
               <l>In the Court, as thou art befriended</l>
               <l> So ſhall thy ſute be ended.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And againe, Better is a friend in the Courte, then a penny in thy purſe. But this was <hi>apud ſeclum pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> in elder times, when Courtiers cared not for pence: but now that prouerb is inuerted; for wee finde that thy peny in thy purſe prooues thy beſt friend in the Court. Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry hawkes flie from empty fiſtes:
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:2678:59"/> and wert thou as good as <hi>Homer</hi> himſelfe, <hi>Si nihil attuleris.</hi> Pierce Pennileſſe, if hee be a ſuter <hi>in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma pauperis,</hi> muſt walke and waite at the gate, to attend opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe, I aſſure my ſelfe, the Lord our God wil not ſuffer the lamentable complaints of the poore afflicted to beate againſt our ſtonie walles, and yron gates in vaine: But he will in his mercies, raiſe vp ſome wiſe <hi>Abigail,</hi> to molifie the niggard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25</note> 
               <hi>Nabals</hi> of this vncharitable age: for howſoeuer that
<hi>Diues,</hi> who is to <note place="margin">Luke 16.</note> be buried in hell, neither heares, nor regardes hunger-ſtarued <hi>Lazarus:</hi> yet his very dogs will licke his ſores, and leſſen his ſorrowes.</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, He that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in the behalfe of the poore, whoſe out-cries rent his heart, whatſoeuer his woordes do worke, and howeſoeuer his ſpeeche dooth proſper, hee hath diſcharged
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:2678:60"/> the dutie of a true Chriſtian neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and hath made manifeſt his mercifulnes, <hi>Miſericordias, à mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſero corde dictas,</hi> and ſeuentie times ſeuen times bleſſed are ſuch mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull <note place="margin">Matth. 5</note> men, for they ſhall be ſure to obtaine mercie.</p>
            <q>And beſought him ſaying, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>By theſe woordes our Catholike brethren of <hi>Rome,</hi> thinke they haue made a great conqueſt ouer vs (as their Annotations in their Rhemiſh Teſtament obſerue) but they tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph before the victory, they doe beare vs downe, hand ouer head, that we ſhall neuer be able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their Doctrine of the Inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Saintes, if this place be wel conſidered: For thus they reaſon, the Diſciples of our Lord Ieſus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeche him, in the behalfe of this poore woman, <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Saints of God make interceſſion for vs. Is it not therefore neceſſary, that wee cal vpon them, to continue this their
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:2678:60"/> interceſſion for vs? An other argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is this; If the Saints of God, compaſſed about with their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities in this militant Church, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one for another, preuayle wyth our Lord Ieſus, howe much more ſhall the Saintes, nowe glorified in the triumphant Church (makeing interceſſion for vs) be heard of our Sauiour?</p>
            <p>But to meet with theſe men, and their reaſons, and (if it be poſſible) to ſatisfie ſuch as be not obdurate in this hereſie: although it be gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallie receiued in the ſchooles, and it goes for good payment amongſt them, that <hi>Argumentum ab exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plis no probat.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> An argument drawne from examples prooues nothing: yet will wee inſiſt in this example, and from hence let vs ſee howe this doctrine may be diduced.</p>
            <p>The Diſciples of our Lorde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate him for this woman: <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Saintes pray for vs<hi>:</hi> and who is he
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:2678:61"/> that denies this Doctrine, ſo it be rightly vnderſtoode (as the nature of the Text leads vs) of the Saints here vpon earth yet aliue, as theſe Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples now were? But to force this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, <hi>à viuis, ad mortuos, ab ente ad non ens,</hi> from the Saints nowe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, amongſt vs inured to infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with vs, to the Saintes dead and departed exempted from the leaſt feeling or touch of any infirmities; is not this a prepoſterous reaſoning? <hi>Numquid viui conſulent mortuos?</hi> ſhall the liuing aske counſell of the dead?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, wee reade that this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man cries out vpon our Lord Ieſus, wee can not probably gather, that ſhe called vpon any of the Apoſtls, or beſought them to intreate our Lord Ieſus for her.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Laſtly, if ſhe did beſeech them, and they at her requeſt did intreate our Lord for her, yet marke, I pray you, how little they preuayle, they
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:2678:61"/> doe not onely not obtayne, but they are repulſed in their requeſt, ſo that by the ſight of this example, we are rather diſcoraged, than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to call vpon the Saints. And whereas for the more gratious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of this doctrine, they talke of Porters, Warders, and many friendly fauorites, who muſt be firſt ſollicited before our Lord Ieſus be acquainted with our petitions; out of doubt, heerein they ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues great ennemies to the free grace of God in our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, and they offer his grace ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt wrongs.</p>
            <p>For, may wee imagine that hee <note place="margin">Reuel. 2.</note> (who now ſtandeth at the doore of our heartes) and knocketh that he may come into vs, and dwell with vs: when wee ſhall knocke at the gate of his mercies, by our feruent and faithfull prayers, will he not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, nor graunt admiſſion vnto our requeſts? Saith not I pray you the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:2678:62"/> Scripture, The Lord is neere vnto all ſuch as call vpon him, yea al ſuch as cal vpon him faithfully, &amp;c. Alſo, do they not know, or will they not vnderſtand, that al our payers oght to be directed to the ſhoot-anker of our faith, and do any chriſtians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in any of the Saints? We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue there are Saintes, as there are Angells, and we beleeue the Saints and Angells, that is, giue credence vnto their words, anſwerable to the truth of holy Scriptures, but to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in the Saints, is to make them our gods, and this were groſſe ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie.</p>
            <p>Then, if it be not lawfull for any chriſtian, to beleeue in the Saintes, neyther is it lawfull to pray vnto the Saintes, for wee muſt pray to them onely, in whom we beleeue.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, ſince the Lord hath ſaid, <note place="margin">Pſalme 50.</note> he that offereth me praiſe, honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me<hi>:</hi> therefore we ſay, he that offereth praiſe or prayer to any but
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:2678:62"/> God alone, he diſhonoureth him. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> We conclude this point, chalenging them to ſhew vs, either any expreſſe commandement throughout the whole Scriptures, which imoyneth vs to call vpon any Angell or Saint departed out of this world: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Or let them ſet vs downe any faithful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, aſſuring vs that we ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile in our petitions, which we make vnto any Angell or Saint de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Or laſtlie, let them prooue to vs, that any of the Patriarkes, Prophets, or Apoſtles of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, made any of their prayers vnto any creature in heauen or earth, ſaue to the Lord onelie, and they ſhall doe ſomewhat for their inuocation of Saintes. But if this cannot be done (or at the leaſt neuer truely done) then are we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to erre ſtill from them in this point of doctrine, and ſo to ſay with the Prophet <hi>Ieremy,</hi> If we be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, thou haſt deceiued vs, ô
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:2678:63"/> Lord, for thou haſt commaunded vs to call vpon thee in the time of trouble, promiſing that thou wilt heare vs, and deliuer vs, that we may glorifie thee: To thee be glorie for it. It followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Send her away]</hi> This is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond point, the ſumme of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, to be rid of her they care not how, ſo they were eaſed of her. Wherein firſt of all we may meet with this prepoſterous pollicie, the ouer weening wiſdom of fleſh and bloud, wherby ſhe thinkes ſhe may out ſtrip the counſell of the Lord. For example, one is bade to goe waſh him ſelfe in <hi>Iordan,</hi> and he <note place="margin">2. Reg. 5.</note> ſhall be cleane; and hee replies, are there not as good and as goodlie waters in <hi>Damaſco?</hi> Another binds the counſell of God to eight dayes, <note place="margin">Iudeth 7.</note> or elſe hee will ſurrender the citie. The bleſſed mother of our Lord <note place="margin">Iohn 2.</note> Ieſus Chriſt will learne him what he hath to doo, and tell him, they
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:2678:63"/> want wine at the mariage. And the choſen Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> will
<note place="margin">Math. 16.</note> not bee behind in kindneſſe, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his maſter, to ſpare him ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtolicall canon is, that <note place="margin">Phil. 4.</note> wee ſhould follow the trueth in loue, wee muſt not out ſtrip the trueth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we muſt follow the trueth, wee muſt not direct the trueth.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, wee muſt follow the trueth, wee muſt not follow our owne conceits, or the deuiſes of our owne braine: but this world is topſie turuie turned, and the world runnes backward. The pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient will preſcribe what the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition ſhall miniſter vnto him; the ſheepe will chooſe and leade their ſhepheard; the diſciples will teach their maſter. Is not this meere madneſſe amongſt the ſonnes of men?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:2678:64"/> Truely ſaid the Prophet, euerie man is a beaſt in his owne vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <note place="margin">Ieremy 7.</note>: and our Prouerb is, <hi>quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſibi peſſimus magiſter,</hi> euery man is a bad Schoolemaiſter vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>We conclude woe vnto him that is wiſe in his owne eyes: let vs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the Lorde leading vs, captiua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting al our vnderſtanding to the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duct and guide of his will. For I aſſure you, the will and pleaſure of God is the exacteſt rule of all wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, equitie and iuſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>[For ſhe crieth after vs.]</hi> This is the third and laſt point, contayning the reaſon of this their requeſt; they deſire to haue her ſhaken off and ſent away, becauſe ſhe maketh ſuch an outcrie, and ſo bawleth out af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them: they regard not ſo much her help, as their owne eaſe, ſo ſhe were gone, that they were no more troubled with her clamorous noiſe, that was all they wiſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:2678:64"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Wherein firſt of all, we ſee how the Lord God turneth the corrupt affections of men, to the good of his children, as a wiſe phiſition in vſing poyſon, which he ſo tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by degrees, that the poyſon, which of it ſelfe is meere hurtfull, by the phiſitions skill, worketh an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect moſt profitable: ſo from the lewdeſt and corrupteſt aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctions of men, the Lord our God produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth good effects: Hence is it that <hi>Auſten</hi> ſaith, <hi>Deus aliquando volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ſuam bonam per voluntatem improborum malam implet,</hi> God ſometime effecteth his good wil, by the naughtie will of the wicked: as that wrongfull impriſonment of
<hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> by that ſlanderous ſurmiſe of <note place="margin">Geneſ. 39.</note>
               <hi>Putiphars</hi> wife, as alſo that vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſale which his brethren made of him. From theſe out-rages the Lord fetcheth forth the meanes of their preſeruation in the needfull time of their trouble.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:2678:65"/> So likewiſe, from the moſt mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous treaſon that euer this worldes eye wondred at, which <hi>Iudas</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, the Lord God wrought, and <note place="margin">Math.
26.</note> brought out the redemption of mankind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> reporteth, that a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, in hope to kill <hi>Pericles,</hi> ſtroke him vpon the ſtomach with a ſtone ſo vehementlie, that the blow brake an impoſtume, bred within him, wherby hee recouered his perfect health: euen ſo the Lord applieth the vngodly proceedings of the wicked vnto a good end. Notable is the ſaying which <hi>Ioſeph</hi> vſeth vnto his brethren, when you thought <note place="margin">Geneſ. 45.</note> euill againſt me, God diſpoſed it to good, that he might worke, as it is come to paſſe this day, and ſaue much people therby.</p>
            <p>The wicked therefore run on in their wickednes, and God runneth with them, not ſtaying their courſe, but turning their way to his glorie,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:2678:65"/> and the good of his elect. Neither haue the vngodlie herein to reioice, becauſe God maketh a profitable vſe of their poyſon-ſom ſinnes, for thou art not therefore to be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, thou vngodlie liuer, becauſe the Lord can conuert thy vngodlines to his good. <hi>Babilon</hi> was his hammer, and <hi>Aſhur</hi> the ſcourge of his wrath: yet both his hammer &amp; his ſcourge (when they had done their offices) were throwne into the fire, and burnt to aſhes. We know that Sathan himſelfe is the executioner of his will and ſeruice, and yet wee <note place="margin">2. Peter 3.</note> know alſo, that Sathan is reſerued in chaines vnder darknes, vnto the iudgement of the great day.</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, The Lord raigneth, be the people neuer ſo mad, he ſitteth aboue the
<hi>Cherubins,</hi> be the wicked neuer ſo outragious, and he ſo rangeth &amp; ruleth all their deuiſes, be they neuer ſo diuiliſh, that they ſhall turne to his glorie,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:2678:66"/> and the benefit of his elect.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Laſtly, in that the Diſciples de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to haue her ſent away, becauſe ſhe crieth after them: Hence are we learned, ſo farre forth to labour and ſeek for our owne eaſe, as it may alſo ſtand with the good of our neighbour, for we are neither borne for our ſelues, nor to our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues: and therfore the prouerb ſaith,</p>
            <q>
               <l>He that liues to himſelfe alone,</l>
               <l>Is worthie to liue with none.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth neuer allowed of two kindes of men, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the louers of them ſelues, nor <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, deſpiſers and haters of men. The Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, Wee are all members of one body, and therefore the eie can <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.</note> not ſay, I haue no need of the hand; nor the hand, I haue no neede of the feete.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Demosthenes</hi> telles the <hi>Athenians</hi> a tale, but it hath his Morall: the members of the body (ſayth the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratour)
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:2678:66"/> once fell at variance amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt themſelues; the eye, he was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, becauſe all that he looked after, was little enough to pleaſe the belly; the handes were offended, becauſe all they did, was little e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to fill the mouth, and ſatisfie the belly; the feete were offended, becauſe all their trauell was for the belly: Thus offended, they agreed euery one to withdrawe his duetie from the belly, ſo that in ſhorte time the belly became hunger-pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and waxed ſo feeble, that the eye ſight failed, the handes ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and the feete trembled vnder their burden: inquiring therefore the cauſe thereof, they found, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from the faintneſſe of the heart, becauſe of the emptineſſe of the belly.</p>
            <p>Wherefore they concluded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelues, that for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery of their former health and happy eſtate, they would ioyne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:2678:67"/> againe, as Nature had taught them: euery one in his place to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the belly.</p>
            <p>The Fable hath his meaning, for God hath knit vs all in a ſociable mu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall bond of kindnes, and it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time falleth out, that the Princely Lion ſtands in neede of the helpe of the ſeely mouſe.</p>
            <p>It is worth the marking, that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> howſoeuer he flies into the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes for his own ſafetie, yet euen there he hath a care of vncourteous <hi>Nabals</hi> welfare: ſee yee not how the <note place="margin">1. Sam 25.</note> heauens vniuerſally droppe downe their kindenes vpon vs all, and the earth generally bringeth foorth her plenty vnto vs all? yet are there a ſort of ſauage menne, that deſire to liue alone vpon th'earth, they ioyne houſe to houſe, and land to land lea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing not the poore, a ſticke, or a ſtone to reſt vppon: the Prouerbe was in the dayes of <hi>Zacharie,</hi> That which dies, let it die; as though the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:2678:67"/> affliction of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> concerned not them.</p>
            <p>In time paſt it was ſayde, <hi>Homo homini deus,</hi> Man was to man a god, in all kindenes and curteous reliefe: but now we prooue it, <hi>Homo homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni daemon,</hi> Man is to man a Diuell, and a dog, diſturbing and deuour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him<hi>:</hi> they ſay, <hi>Lupilupum non laniant,</hi> One Wolfe preyes not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an other, and ſhall one man, nay more, one chriſtian, nay moſt one brother, for we haue al one Father in Heauen, and one mother (the Church) in earth, ſhall theſe ſeeke the ruine, ſpoyle, &amp; vndoing one of an other? this is monſtrous in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, prepoſterous in religion, and diueliſh in the ſight of God, and all good men.</p>
            <p>Our concluſion is, with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, Be ye all of one mind, loue as brethren, let euery man ſo far ſeeke <note place="margin">2. Corin. 23.</note> his owne priuate eaſe, as it hurteth not the publike good of any man,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:2678:68"/> that the priuate affections of your owne profite, prooue not the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall afflictions of your neighbours; ſo ſhall God be glorified, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth comforted and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened: And this ſhalbe the crown of our ioy, euen the teſtimony of a good conſcience in all thinges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and man, which God for his ſonne Chriſt Ieſus ſake graunt vnto vs all Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>Finis Sectionis primae partis.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>52. line 21. for defenſing, read defenſiue.</p>
            <p>53. line 24. for gratious, read grant our.</p>
            <p>94. line vlt. for Paruus, read Prauus.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2678:68"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
